<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Delightes for ladies to adorne their persons, tables, closets, and distillatories with beauties, banquets, perfumes and waters.</title>
            <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22095229</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22095229</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25027</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25027)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1733:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Delightes for ladies to adorne their persons, tables, closets, and distillatories with beauties, banquets, perfumes and waters.</title>
                  <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[192] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Short,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Reade, practise, and censure."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H¹².</note>
                  <note>Text within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Recipes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cosmetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DELIGHTES for Ladies, to adorne their Perſons, Tables, cloſets, and diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latories: <hi>WITH</hi> Beauties, banquets, perfumes and Waters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reade, practiſe, and cenſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Peter Short. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:2"/>
            <head>To all true louers of Arte and knowledge.</head>
            <l>SOmetimes I writ the formes of burning balles,</l>
            <l>Supplying wants that were by woodfals wrought</l>
            <l>Sometimes of tubs defended ſo by Arte,</l>
            <l>As fire in vaine hath their deſtruction ſought:</l>
            <l>Sometimes I writ of laſting Beuerage,</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Neptune</hi> and his Pilgrims to content:</l>
            <l>Sometimes of foode, ſweete, freſh, and durable,</l>
            <l>To maintaine life when all things els were ſpent:</l>
            <l>Sometimes I writ of ſundrie ſorts of ſoile,</l>
            <l>Which neither <hi>Ceres</hi> nor her handmaids knew,</l>
            <l>I writ to all, but ſcarſly one beleeues</l>
            <l>Saue <hi>Diue</hi> and <hi>Denſhire</hi> who haue ſound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true</l>
            <l>When heauens did mourne in cloudy mantles clad,</l>
            <l>And threatned famine to the ſonnes of men:</l>
            <l>VVhen ſobbing earth denide her kindly fruit</l>
            <l>To painefull ploughman and his bindes, euen then</l>
            <l>I writ relieuing remedies of dearth,</l>
            <l>That Arte might helpe where nature made a ſaile:</l>
            <l>But all in vaine theſe new borne babes of Arte,</l>
            <l>In their vntimelie birth ſtraight way do quaile.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:3"/>Of theſe and ſuch like other newe found skils,</l>
            <l>VVith painfull pen I whilome writ at large,</l>
            <l>Expecting ſtill my Countries good therein,</l>
            <l>And not reſpecting labour, time, or charge.</l>
            <l>But now my pen and paper are perfum'd,</l>
            <l>I ſcorne to write with Coppres or with galle,</l>
            <l>Barbarian canes are now become my quils,</l>
            <l>Roſewater is the inke I write withall:</l>
            <l>Of ſweetes the ſweeteſt I will now commend,</l>
            <l>To ſweeteſt creatures that the earth doth beare:</l>
            <l>Theſe are the Saints to whom I ſacrifice</l>
            <l>Preſerues and conſerues both of plum and peare.</l>
            <l>Empalings now adew, tuſh marchpaine wals</l>
            <l>Are ſtrong enough, and beſt be fits our age:</l>
            <l>Let piercing bullets turne to ſugar bals:</l>
            <l>The Spaniſh féare is huſht and all their rage.</l>
            <l>Of Marmelade and paſte of Genua,</l>
            <l>Of musked ſugars I intend to wright:</l>
            <l>Of Leach, of Sucket, and Quidinia,</l>
            <l>Affording to each Lady her delight.</l>
            <l>I teach both fruits and flowers to preſerue,</l>
            <l>And candie them, ſo Nutmegs, cloues and mace:</l>
            <l>To make both marchpaine paſte, and ſugred plate,</l>
            <l>And caſt the ſame in formes of ſweeteſt grace.</l>
            <l>Each bird and foule ſo moulded from the life,</l>
            <l>And after caſt in ſweet compounds of arte,</l>
            <l>As if the fleſh and forme which nature gaue,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:3"/>Did ſtill remaine in euerie lim and part.</l>
            <l>When chryſtall froſts haue nipt the tender grape,</l>
            <l>And cleane conſum'd the fruits of euerie vine,</l>
            <l>Yet here behold the cluſters freſh and faire,</l>
            <l>Fed from the branch, or hang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng on the line,</l>
            <l>The walnut, ſmall nut, and the Cheſnut ſweete,</l>
            <l>Whoſe ſugred kernels looſe their pleaſing taſte,</l>
            <l>Are here from yeere to yeere preſerued,</l>
            <l>And made by Arte with ſtrongeſt fruites to laſt.</l>
            <l>Th'artichoke, the apple of ſuch ſtrength,</l>
            <l>The Quince, Pomegranate, with the Barberie,</l>
            <l>No ſugar vs'd, yet colour, taſte, and ſmell,</l>
            <l>Are here maintain'd and kept moſt naturally.</l>
            <l>For Ladies cloſets and their ſtillatories,</l>
            <l>Both waters, ointments, and ſweet ſmelling bals,</l>
            <l>In eaſie termes without affected ſpeech,</l>
            <l>Theere preſent moſt ready at their cals.</l>
            <l>And leaſt with careleſſe pen I ſhould omit,</l>
            <l>The wrongs that nature on their perſons wrought,</l>
            <l>Or parching ſunne with his hot firie rayes,</l>
            <l>For theſe likewiſe, relieuing meanes I ſought.</l>
            <l>No idle thoughts, nor vaine ſurmiſed skils,</l>
            <l>By fancie framde within a theorique braine,</l>
            <l>My muſe preſents vnto your ſacred eares,</l>
            <l>To win your fauours falſly, I diſdaine.</l>
            <l>From painfull practiſe, from experience,</l>
            <l>A ſound though coſtly myſteries I deriue</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>VVith firy flames in ſcorching <hi>Vulcans</hi> forge,</l>
            <l>To teaſt and fine each ſecret I do ſtriue:</l>
            <l>Accept them well and let my wearied muſe</l>
            <l>Repoſe her ſelfe in Ladies laps a while,</l>
            <l>So when ſhee wakes, ſhe happely may record,</l>
            <l>Her ſweeteſt dreames in ſome more pleaſing ſtile.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>H. Plat.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:4"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOod Reader, for the vnderſtanding of this Table, know that</hi> a, b, c, d, <hi>do giue dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions vnto the foure ſeuerall parts or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of this Booke,</hi> (a) <hi>for the firſt, the reſt in their order.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>AENula Campana rootes preſerued. a, 1</item>
               <item>Almonds in Leach a, 27.</item>
               <item>Almond butter to make a, 57</item>
               <item>Almonds into gelly a, 58</item>
               <item>Alliger diſtilled b, 16</item>
               <item>Apples kept drie all the yeare a, 47</item>
               <item>Aqua rubea. b, 7</item>
               <item>Aqua compoſita of D. Steuens b, 8</item>
               <item>Artichokes kept long. a, 69</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>BAgs ſweet to lie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt linnen. d, 35</item>
               <item>Ball to take out ſtaines d, 3</item>
               <item>Ball to waſh with d, 8</item>
               <item>Balme water. b, 5</item>
               <item>Beaumanger. c, 11</item>
               <item>Beefe roaſted kept long. c, 18</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:5"/>Beefe powdered kept long without charge. c. 19</item>
               <item>Beefe freſh at the ſea. c. 20</item>
               <item>Beautie for the face. d. 7.14</item>
               <item>Bisket bread or French bisket. a. 19</item>
               <item>Bisket called prince bisket a. 20</item>
               <item>Bisket called biskettello. a. 21</item>
               <item>Bloud of hearbes. b. 22</item>
               <item>Borage candied. a. 11</item>
               <item>Botling of beere truly. c. 27</item>
               <item>Bottles muſtie helped, c. 28</item>
               <item>Bottle ale moſt excellent. c. 32</item>
               <item>Brawne to eat tender and delicat. c. 13</item>
               <item>Broome capers preſerued. a. 37</item>
               <item>Broyling without ſmoake. c. 26</item>
               <item>Bruſe helped. d. 24</item>
               <item>Butter taſting of ſpice or flowers. c. 21</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>Cakes ſweete without ſpice or ſugar. a. 60</item>
               <item>Candying of flowers. a. 9.53</item>
               <item>Candying in rocke candie. a, 33.42</item>
               <item>Candying of Orenge pilles. a. 35</item>
               <item>Candles for Ladies tables. c. 39</item>
               <item>Candles hanging in the aire. c. 40</item>
               <item>Capers of broome preſerued. a. 37</item>
               <item>Capon boyled in white broth. c. 5</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:5"/>Caſting in ſugar plate. a, 13</item>
               <item>Caſting of ſugar in partie moldes. a, 43</item>
               <item>Caſting and molding of fruit. a, 44.</item>
               <item>Cheries preſerued. a, 8</item>
               <item>Cherie pulpe kept dry all the yeere. a 45</item>
               <item>Cheries dried in the ſunne. a, 46</item>
               <item>Cheeſe extraordinarie. c, 22</item>
               <item>Cheſnuts kept long. a, 73</item>
               <item>Chilblaines helped. d, 15</item>
               <item>Chine of veale or chicken boiled. c. 10</item>
               <item>Cinamon water. b, 10</item>
               <item>Collis white and like gellie. a, 55</item>
               <item>Comfits of all ſorts. a, 54</item>
               <item>Conſerue of Prunes or da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſons. a. 50, 52</item>
               <item>Conſerue of Strawberies. a, 51</item>
               <item>Cowcumbers preſerued. a, 36</item>
               <item>Cowſlep paſte. a, 40</item>
               <item>Cowſlip water or vineger of the colour of the cowſlep. c. 34</item>
               <item>Crayfiſh kept long. c. 31</item>
               <item>Creame clowted c. 23</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>DAmaske powder. d, 1, 9</item>
               <item>Damſons in marmelade. a, 31</item>
               <item>Damſon pulpe kept all the yeare. a, 45</item>
               <item>Damſons in conſerue. a, 50, 52</item>
               <item>Dentifriſes for the teeth. d, 26</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:6"/>Diſtillation of hearbes in a new maner. b, 11</item>
               <item>Drying of fruits in the ſun a, 46</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>EGlantine water b, 20</item>
               <item>Eringo rootes preſerued. a, 1</item>
               <item>Extract of vegetables. b, 19</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>FAce ſpotted or freckled to help. d, 6 23</item>
               <item>Face made faire d, 7.14</item>
               <item>Face full of heat helped. d, 11, 16 17, 18, 19, 20, 21</item>
               <item>Face kept white and cleere d, 12</item>
               <item>Fiſh into paſte c, 14</item>
               <item>Fiſh fried kept long c, 17</item>
               <item>Fleſh kept ſweete in ſummer c, 24</item>
               <item>Flies kept from oile peeces c, 30</item>
               <item>Flounder boyled on the french faſhion c, 3</item>
               <item>Flowers preſerued a, 7</item>
               <item>Flowers candied a, 9, 11</item>
               <item>Flowers in rocke candie. a, 42</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:6"/>Flowers dried without wrinkling a, 63</item>
               <item>Fruit preſerued a, 8</item>
               <item>Fruit how to molde and caſt a, 44</item>
               <item>Fruit kept drie all the yeare. a, 45, 46.47</item>
               <item>Fruit kept long freſh. a, 70</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>GEllie chryſtalline a, 26</item>
               <item>Gelly of fruits a, 29</item>
               <item>Gelly of Almonds a, 58</item>
               <item>Gilloflowers kept long a, 61</item>
               <item>Gillowflowers preſerued a, 7</item>
               <item>Gilloflower water b, 20</item>
               <item>Gingerbread a, 22</item>
               <item>Gingerbread drie a, 23</item>
               <item>Ginger in rocke candie a, 33.42</item>
               <item>Ginger greene in ſirup a, 49</item>
               <item>Ginger candied a, 53</item>
               <item>Gloues to perſume d, 34</item>
               <item>Gooſeberies preſerued a, 8</item>
               <item>Grapes growing all the yeere a, 62</item>
               <item>Grapes kept till Eaſter a, 64</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>HAndwater excellent d, 2, 28</item>
               <item>Hands ſtained to helpe. d, 5</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:7"/>Hands freckled to helpe. d, 6</item>
               <item>Handwater of Scotland b, 21</item>
               <item>Haſell nuts kept long a, 72</item>
               <item>Haire blacke altered d, 30, 37</item>
               <item>Haire made yellow. d, 36</item>
               <item>Hearbs diſtilled in a new maner. b, 11</item>
               <item>Hearbs to yeeld ſalt b, 12</item>
               <item>Hearbs to yeeld bloud b, 22</item>
               <item>Honey to yeeld ſpirit b, 13</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>IRiſh Aqua vitae b, 9</item>
               <item>Iſop diſtilled in a new maner b, 11</item>
               <item>Iuice of Orenges or lemmons kept all the yeare. c, 35</item>
               <item>Iumbolds to make a, 16</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>LArkes to boile c, 4</item>
               <item>Lauender diſtilled in a new maner. b 11</item>
               <item>Leach of almonds a 27</item>
               <item>Leach a, 59</item>
               <item>Leg of mutton boiled after the French faſhion c, 7</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:7"/>Lemmons in Marmelade a, 41</item>
               <item>Lemmon moulded and caſt a, 44</item>
               <item>Lemmon iuyce kept all the yeere c, 35</item>
               <item>Lettuce in ſucket a, 32</item>
               <item>Liquerice paſte a, 40</item>
               <item>Lobſters kept long c, 31</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>MAce in rocke candie a, 42</item>
               <item>Mallard to boile c, 6</item>
               <item>Marchpaine paſte a, 12, 18</item>
               <item>Marigolds preſerued a, 7</item>
               <item>Marigolds candied a, 9, 11</item>
               <item>Marigold paſte a, 40</item>
               <item>Marmelade of Quinces or Damſons, a, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Marmelade of Lemmons of Orenges. a, 41</item>
               <item>May deaw clarified d, 33</item>
               <item>Morphew helped d, 21, 22</item>
               <item>Mulberies in gellie a, 29</item>
               <item>Muske ſugar a, 2</item>
               <item>Muſtard meale c, 25</item>
               <item>Muſtineſſe helped or preuented in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters b, 24</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:8"/>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>NVtmegs in rocke candie. a, 33, 42</item>
               <item>Nutmegs candied a, 53</item>
               <item>Nuts molded and caſt off a, 44</item>
               <item>Nuts kept long a, 72</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>ORenges preſerued. a, 34</item>
               <item>Orenge pilles candied a, 35</item>
               <item>Orenges in marmelade a, 41</item>
               <item>Orenge molded and caſt off a, 44</item>
               <item>Orenge iuice kept all the yeere c, 35</item>
               <item>Oiſters kept long. c. 15</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>PAſte of flowers a, 14, 40</item>
               <item>Paſte of Nouie a, 15</item>
               <item>Paſte to keepe one moiſt a, 17</item>
               <item>Paſte called puſt paſte a, 24</item>
               <item>Paſte ſhort without butter a, 25</item>
               <item>Paſte of Genua of Quinces a, 30</item>
               <item>Paſte of fiſh c, 14</item>
               <item>Peare molded and caſt off a, 44</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Peares kept drie a, 47</item>
               <item>Perfumes delicate, and ſodainly made. d, 31</item>
               <item>Perfuming of gloues d, 34</item>
               <item>Pickerel boiled on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> french faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. c, 3</item>
               <item>Pigeons of ſugar paſte a, 10</item>
               <item>Pigeons boiled with Rice c, 9</item>
               <item>Pig to ſowſe c, 1, 2</item>
               <item>Pigs petitoes boiled after the French faſhion c, 8</item>
               <item>Plums preſerued a, 8</item>
               <item>Plums dried in the ſunne a, 46</item>
               <item>Pomander to make d, 4</item>
               <item>Pomander renewed d, 32</item>
               <item>Pomatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the face. d, 13</item>
               <item>Pomgranats kept long a, 68</item>
               <item>Pieſeruing of Roots a, 1</item>
               <item>Preſeruing of cowcumbers a, 36</item>
               <item>Prunes in conſerue a, 50, 52</item>
               <item>Pulpe of fruit kept all the yeare. a, 45</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>QVidinia of Quinces a, 28</item>
               <item>Quinces into paſte of Genua. a, 30</item>
               <item>Quinces in marmelade, a, 31</item>
               <item>Quinces kept drie all the yeare. a, 47</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:9"/>Quinces kept long. a, 67</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Rabbets of ſugar paſte. a, 10</item>
               <item>Raſpices in gellie. a, 29</item>
               <item>Rootes preſerued, a, 1</item>
               <item>Rootes candied a, 53</item>
               <item>Roſa ſolis to make b, 6</item>
               <item>Roſemarie flowers candied. a, 9</item>
               <item>Roſeleaues to drie. a, 3, 6</item>
               <item>Roſe ſirup, a, 5</item>
               <item>Roſes preſerued. a, 7</item>
               <item>Roſes and Roſe leaues candied. a, 9, 11</item>
               <item>Roſe paſte. a, 40</item>
               <item>Roſes kept long. a, 61</item>
               <item>Roſe leaues dried without wrinckles. a, 63</item>
               <item>Roſewater diſtilled at Michaelmas. b, 14</item>
               <item>Roſewater diſtilled in a ſpeedy man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r. b, 15</item>
               <item>Roſes to yeeld a ſpirit. b, 17</item>
               <item>Roſewater moſt excellent b, 18</item>
               <item>Roſewater, and yet the Roſeleaues not diſcoloured. b, 23</item>
               <item>Roſewater and oyle drawne together. b. 25</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:9"/>Roſewater of the colour of the Roſe. c, 34</item>
               <item>Roſe vineger of the colour of the Roſe. c, 34</item>
               <item>Roſe vineger made in a newe manner. c, 41</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>SAlet oile purified and graced in taſte and ſmell. c, 36</item>
               <item>Salmon kept long freſh c, 16</item>
               <item>Salt of hearbs b, 12</item>
               <item>Salt delicate for the Table c, 38</item>
               <item>Sawſedges of Polonia c, 12</item>
               <item>Sirup of Violets a, 4</item>
               <item>Sirup of Roſes a, 5</item>
               <item>Sparrowes to boile. c, 4</item>
               <item>Spirit of wine extraordinarie b, 1</item>
               <item>Spirit of wine ordinarie b, 2</item>
               <item>Spirits of Spices b, 3</item>
               <item>Spirit of wine taſting of any vegetable. b, 4</item>
               <item>Spirit of honey b, 13</item>
               <item>Spirit of hearbs and flowers b, 17</item>
               <item>Skin white and cleare d, 2</item>
               <item>Sunburning helped d, 22</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:10"/>Stoue to ſweate in, d, 27</item>
               <item>Strawberies in gellie a, 29</item>
               <item>Strawberies in conſerue a, 51</item>
               <item>Sucket of Lettuce ſtalkes a, 32</item>
               <item>Sucket of greene walnuts a, 49</item>
               <item>Sugar musked a, 2</item>
               <item>Sugar paſte for foule a, 10</item>
               <item>Sugar plate to caſt in a, 13</item>
               <item>Sugar plate of flowers a, 14</item>
               <item>Sugar plate to colour a, 38</item>
               <item>Sugar caſt in partie molds a, 43</item>
               <item>Sugar ſmelling and taſting of the cloue or cynamon. a, 71</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>TEale to boile c, 6</item>
               <item>Teeth kept white and ſound d, 10 25, 26</item>
               <item>Time diſtilled in a new maner b, 11</item>
               <item>Troſſes for the ſea a, 39</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>VIneger diſtilled b, 16</item>
               <item>Vineger to clarifie c, 37</item>
               <item>Violet ſirup. a, 4</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:10"/>Violet paſte a, 40, 14</item>
               <item>Violet water or vineger of the colour of the violet c, 34</item>
               <item>Vſquebath b, 9</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>VV</head>
               <item>WAfers to make a, 56</item>
               <item>Walnuts in ſucket a, 49</item>
               <item>Walnuts kept freſh long a, 65.66</item>
               <item>Wardens kept drie all the yeare. a, 47</item>
               <item>Waſhing water ſweete. b, 21, d, 2, 28, 29</item>
               <item>Whites of egges broken ſpeedily. c, 29</item>
               <item>Wigin to boyle c, 6</item>
               <item>Wine taſting of wormwood made ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily. c, 33</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Y</head>
               <item>Ytch helped. d, 25.21.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:11"/>
            <head>The Arte of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, conſeruing, candying, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> How to preſerue Eringo roots, Aenula Campana, and ſo of others in the ſame manner</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth them til they be tender, then take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay the piths of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and leaue them in a cola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der til they haue dropped as much as they will, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing a thin ſirup ready, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being cold into the ſirup being alſo colde, and let them ſtand ſo three dayes, then boyle the ſirup (adding ſome more freſh ſirup vnto it to ſupply that which the roots haue drunk vp) a little high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and at three dayes end boyle the ſirup againe without anie new addition, vnto the full height of a preſeruing ſirup, and put in your roots, and ſo keepe them. Rootes
<pb facs="tcp:25027:12"/>preſerued in this maner will eate verie tender, becauſe they neuer boiled in the ſirup.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> How to make muske ſugar of common ſugar.</head>
               <p>BRuſe 4 or 6. graines of muske, place them in a peece of ſarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, fine lawne or cambricke dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, lay this in the bottome of a gallie pot, ſtraining your Sugar thereon, ſtop your pot cloſe, and all the ſugar in a fewe dayes will both ſent and taſte of muske, and when you haue ſpent that ſugar, you may lay more ſugar thereon, which will alſo receiue the like impreſsion. Such muske ſugar is fold for two ſhillings the pound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> How to drie Roſeleaues in a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent maner.</head>
               <p>WHen you haue newly taken out your breade, then put
<pb facs="tcp:25027:12"/>in your Roſes in a ſieue firſt clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping away the whites, that they may be all of one colour, lay them about one inch in thickneſſe in the ſieue, &amp; when they haue ſtood halfe an houre or therabout they will growe whitiſh on the top, let them yet remaine without ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring till the vppermoſt of them be fully dried, then ſtir the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together, and leaue them about one other halfe houre, and if you finde them drie in the top, ſtir them together againe, &amp; ſo continue this worke vntill they bee throughly dried, then put them hote as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an earthen pot hauing a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row mouth, and being wel leaded within, (the Refiners of gold and ſiluer, call theſe pottes hookers) ſtop it with corke, and wet parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or with Waxe and Roſen mixed together, and hang your pot in a chimney or neere a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall fire, &amp; ſo they will keep ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding faire in color &amp; moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate
<pb facs="tcp:25027:13"/>in ſente. And if you feare their relenting, take the Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues about Candlemas, and put them once again into a ſieue ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them vp and downe often til they be drie, and then put them vp againe hote into your potte. Note that you muſt ſet vp your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen lidde, but not lute it about when you ſet in your Roſeleaues, either the firſt or ſecond time. <hi>poſt. numero 6.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> A moſt excellent ſirup of Violets, both in taſte and tincture.</head>
               <p>EXpreſſe the iuice of clipt Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, &amp; to three parts of iuice take one fourth parte of conduit water, put the ſame into an Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſter morter, with the leaues vvhich you haue ſtamped, and wring the ſame out through a cloth, as you did at the firſt into the other iuice, put thereto a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proportion of the fineſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:25027:13"/>and brought alſo into a moſt fine powder, let the ſame ſtand 10. or 12. houres in a cleane glaſed earthen pan, then draine away the cleareſt, and put it into a glaſſe, and put therto a fewe drops of the iuice of Lemmons, and it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come cleare, tranſparent, and of the violet colour. Then you may expreſſe more iuice into the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, which will ſettle in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, with ſome of the thickeſt part of the iuyce: and heating the ſame vpon a gentle fire, it will alſo becom a good ſirup of violets, but not comparable to the firſt. By this manner of worke you gaine one quarter of ſirup more then diuers Apothecaries doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>5. A</hi> ſingular manner of making the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of Roſes.</head>
               <p>FILL a ſiluer baſon three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters full of raine water, or roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, put therein a conuenient
<pb facs="tcp:25027:14"/>proportion of Roſe leaues, couer the baſon and ſet it vpon a pot of hote water (as wee vſually bake a Cuſtard) in three quarters of an houre, or one whole houre at the moſt, you ſhall purchaſe the whole ſtrength and tincture of the Roſe, then take out thoſe leaues, wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out all their liquor gently, and ſteepe more freſhe leaues in the ſame water, continue this iterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeuen times, and then make it vp in a ſirup, &amp; this ſirup worketh more kindely then that which is made meerely of the iuyce of the Roſe. You may make ſundry other ſirups in this manner. <hi>Quaere</hi> of hanging a pewter heade ouer the baſon, if the aſcending water will be worth the keeping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Another way for the drying of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues.</head>
               <p>DRie them in the heat of a hot ſunnie daye vppon a Leades,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:14"/>turning them vp and downe till they be drie (as they doe haie) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put them vp into glaſſes well ſtopt and luted, keeping your glaſſes in warme pleaces, and thus you may keepe all flowers: but hearbs after they are dryed in this manner, are beſt kept in paper bags, placing the bags in cloſe Cupboards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> How to preſerue whole Roſes, Gillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowers, Marigolds, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>DIp a Roſe that is neither in the bud nor ouerblowne, in a ſirrup, conſiſting of ſugar double refined, and Roſewater boiled to his true height, then open the leaues one by one, with a fine ſmooth bodkin either of bone or wood, and preſently if it be a hot ſunnie day, and whileſt the ſunne is in ſome good height, lay them on papers in the ſunne, or elſe
<pb facs="tcp:25027:15"/>drie them with ſome gentle heate in a cloſe roome, heating y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roome before you ſet them in, or in an Ouen vpon papers, in pewter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, &amp; then put them vp in glaſſes and keepe them in drie cupbords neere the fire. You muſt take out the ſeedes if you meane to eate them. You may prooue this, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing with ſugar candie, in ſtead of ſugar if you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> The most kindly waye to preſerue plums, cherries, gooſberies, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt firſt purchaſe ſome reaſonable quantitie of their owne iuice, with a gentle heate vpon imbers between two diſhes, diuiding the iuice ſtill as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the ſtewing, then boyle each fruit in his owne iuice, with a conuenient proportion of the beſt refined ſugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>9,</hi> How to candie Reſemarie flowers. Roſe leaues, Roſes, Marigolds, &amp;c. with preſeruation of colour.</head>
               <p>DIſtolue refined, or double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined ſugar, or ſugar candy it ſelfe in a little Roſewater, boyle it to a reaſonable hight, put in your rootes or flowers when you ſirup is either fully cold, or almoſt cold, let them reſt therein till the ſirup haue pearced them ſufficientlie, then take out your flowers with a skimmer, ſuffering the looſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup to run from them as longe as it will, boyl that ſirup a little more and put in more flowers as before, diuide them alſo, then boyle all the ſirup which remaineth and is not drunke vp in the flowers, to the height of <hi>manus Chriſti,</hi> putting in more ſugar if you ſee cauſe, but no more Roſewater, put your flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers therein vvhen your ſirup is cold or almoſt cold, and let them ſtand till they candie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> A moſt delicate and ſtiffe ſugar paſte whereof to caſt Rabbets, Pigeons, or any other little birde or beaſt, either from the life or carued molds.</head>
               <p>FIrſt diſſolue Iſinglaſſe in faire water or with ſome Roſewater in the latter ende, then beate blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched almonds as you woulde for marchpane ſtuffe, and drawe the ſame with creame, and Roſewater (milke will ſerue, but creame is more delicate) then put therein ſome powdered ſugar, into which you may diſſolue your Iſinglaſſe beeing firſt made into gellie, in faire warme water) note, the more Iſinglaſſe you put therein, the ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your worke will prooue) then hauing your rabbets, woodcocke, &amp;c. molded either in plaiſter from life, or elſe carued in wood (firſt annointing your wodden moldes with oyle of ſweete almonds, and your plaiſter or ſtone moldes with
<pb facs="tcp:25027:16"/>barrowes greaſe) poure your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-paſte thereon. A quarte of creame, a quarterne of almonds, 2. ounces of Iſinglaſſe, and 4. or 6. ounces of ſugar, is a reaſonable good proportion for this ſtuffe. <hi>Quaere</hi> of moulding your Birdes, Rabbets, &amp;c. in the compounde wax mentioned in my <hi>Iewel houſe,</hi> in the title of the <hi>arte of moulding &amp; caſting, pag.</hi> 60. For ſo your moulds will laſt long. You may dredge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your foule with cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of bread, cinamon and ſugar boyled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo they wil ſeem as if they were roſted and breaded. Leach &amp; gelly may be caſt in this manner. This paſte you may alſo driue with a fine rowling pin, as ſmooth &amp; as thin as you pleaſe; it laſteth not long, &amp; therefore it muſt be eaten within a fewe dayes after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof. By this meanes a ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet may be preſented in the form of a ſupper, beeing a verie rare and ſtrange deuiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11</hi> To ſandie Marigolds, Roſes, Borage, or Roſemary flowers.</head>
               <p>BOyle Sugar and Roſewater a little vpon a chaſing diſh with coales, then put the flowers (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings throughly dryed, either by the ſunne or on the fire) into the ſugar, and boyle them a little, then ſtrewe the powder of double refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſugar vpon them, and turne them, and let them boyle a little longer, taking the diſh from the fire, then ſtrew more powdred ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar on the contrarie ſide of the flower. Theſe will drie of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in two or three houres in a hate ſunny day, thogh they ly not in the ſunne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> To make an excellent Marchpane paſte, to print off in molds for banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting diſhes.</head>
               <p>TAke to euerie Iordan almond blanched, three ſpoonfuls of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:17"/>the whiteſt refined ſugar you can get, ſearce your ſugar, and now and then as you ſee cauſe put in 2. or three drops of damaske Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, beate the ſame in a ſmooth ſtone morter, with great labor, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you haue brought it into a dry ſtiffe paſte, one quarterne of ſugar is ſufficient to worke at once.</p>
               <p>Make your paſte into little bals, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ball containing ſo much by eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as will couer your mold or printe, then rowle the ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a rowling pin, vppon a ſheete of cleane paper without ſtrewing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie powdered ſugar either vpon your paſte or paper. There is a countrie Gentlewoman whome I could name, which venteth great ſtore of ſugar cakes made of this compoſition. But the onely fault which I finde in this paſte is, that it taſteth too much of the ſugar, and too little of the almonds, and therefore you may proue the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof with ſuch almonds,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:18"/>which haue had ſome part of their oyle taken from them by expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, before you incorporate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſugar, and ſo happely you may mixe a greater quantitie of them with the ſugar, becauſe they are not ſo oily as the other. You may mixe cinamon or ginger in your paſte, &amp; that will both grace the taſte, and alter the colour; but the ſpice muſt paſſe through a fair fearce: you may ſteepe your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds in colde water all night, &amp; ſo blanch them colde, and being blanched, drie them in a ſieue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the fire. Here the garble of almonds will make a cheap paſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> The making of ſugar-pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting thereof in carued moldes.</head>
               <p>TAke one pound of the whiteſt refined or double refined ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, if you can get it, put thereto three ounces (ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fit-makers,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:18"/>put 6. ounces for more gaine) of the beſt ſtarch you can buy, and if you dry the ſugar after it is pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, it will the ſooner paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough your lawne ſearce: then ſearce it &amp; lay the ſame on a heape in the midſt of a ſheet of clean pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: in the middle of which maſſe, put a pretie lump of the bignes of a walnut of gum dragagant, firſt ſteeped in Roſewater one night; a porenger ful of roſewater is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to diſſolue one ounce of gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which muſt firſt bee well picked, leauing out the droſſe) remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to ſtraine the gumme through a canuas, then hauing mixed ſom of the white of an egge with your ſtrained gum, temper it with the ſugar betwixt your fingers by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little, til you haue wrought vpp all the ſugar and the gumme together into a ſtiffe paſte, and in the tempring let there be alwaies ſome of the ſugar betweene your fingers and the gumme, then duſt
<pb facs="tcp:25027:19"/>your wodden moulds a little with ſome of that powdered ſugar tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a peece of Lawne or fine linnen cloath, and hauing driuen out with your rowling pin a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient portion of your paſte to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thicknes, couer your mold therewith, preſſing the ſame down into euery hollow parte of your molde with your fingers, &amp; when it hath taken the whole impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, knocke the mold on the edge againſt a table, and the paſte will iſſue forth with the impreſſion of the molde vpon it: or if the molde be deepe cut, you may put in the pointe of your knife gently into the deepeſt parts heere and there, lifting vpp by little and little the paſte out of the molde. And if in the making of this paſte, you hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to put-in too much gum, you may put more ſugar thereto, and if too much ſugar, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more gum: you muſt alſo worke this paſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your molds, as ſpeedily as you
<pb facs="tcp:25027:19"/>can after it is once made, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it harden, and if it growe ſo harde that it cracke, mixe more gum therwith. Cut away with your knife from the edges of your paſte all thoſe peeces which haue no parte of the worke vpon them, and worke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp with the paſte which remaineth; and if you will make ſawcers, diſhes, boawls, &amp;c. then (hauing firſt driuen out your paſte vpon paper, firſt duſted ouer with ſugar to a conuenient largeneſſe and thickneſſe) put the paſte into ſome ſaucer, diſh, or boawle of a good faſhion, and with your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger preſſe it gently downe to the inſides thereof, till it reſemble the ſhape of the diſh, then pare away the edges with a knife, euen with the skirt of your diſh, or ſawcer, and ſet it againſt the fire till it bee drie on the inſide, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a knife get it out as they vſe to doe a diſh of butter, and drie the backſide; then guilde it on the edges with
<pb facs="tcp:25027:20"/>the white of an egge laide round about the brim of the diſh with a penfill, and preſſe the gold downe with ſome cotton, and when it is dry skew or bruſh off the golde with the foote of an Hare or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. And if you woulde haue your paſt exceeding ſmooth, as to make cardes and ſuch like conceiptes thereof, then roule your paſte vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a ſli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed paper with a ſmooth &amp; poliſhed rowling pin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>14. A</hi> way to make ſugar-plate both of colour and taſte of any flower.</head>
               <p>TAke Violets and beat them in a mortar with a little hard ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, then put into it a ſufficient quantitie of Roſewater, then lay your gum in ſteepe in the water, &amp; ſo worke it into paſte, &amp; ſo wil your paſte be both of the colour of the violet, and of the ſmell of the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. In like ſort may you work with Marigolds, Cowſlips, Primroſes, Bugloſſe or any other flower.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> To make paſte of Nouie.</head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of a pounde of Valentian almonds, otherwiſe called the ſmall almonds or Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie almonds, and beate them in a mortar til they come to paſte, then take ſtale Manchet beeing grated, and drie it before the fire in a diſh, then fift it, then beat it with your almondes, put in the beating of it a litle cinamon, gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the iuyce of a Lemmon, &amp; when it is beaten to perfit paſte, printe it w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your moldes, &amp; ſo dry it in an ouen after you haue drawn out your bread: this paſte will laſt all the yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> To make Iumbolds.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pound of almonds beeing beaten to paſte with a ſhort cake beeing grated, &amp; 2. egs, 2. ounces of cároway ſeeds, being
<pb facs="tcp:25027:21"/>beaten, and the iuice of a Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, &amp; beeing brought into paſte roule it into round ſtrings, then caſte it into knots, and ſo bake it in an ouen, and when they are ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yee them with Roſewater and ſugar, and the white of an egge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten together, then take a feather and guilde them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put them againe into the Ouen, and let them ſtande in a little while, and they will be yced cleane ouer with a white yce, and ſo box them vp, and you may keep them all the yeere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> To make a paſte to keepe you moiſt, if you liſt not to drinke oft, whi h La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies vſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> carrie with them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ride abroad.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pound of damaske prunes &amp; a quartern of dates, ſtone them both, and beate them in a mortar with one warden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing roſted, or elſe a ſlice of olde
<pb facs="tcp:25027:21"/>marmelade and ſo print it in your moldes, and drie it after you haue drawne bread, put ginger vnto it, and you may ſerue it in at a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>18. To</hi> make a Marchpane.</head>
               <p>TAke two poundes of Almonds being blanched and dryed in a ſieue ouer the fire, beate them in a ſtone mortar, and when they bee ſmall mixe with them two pounde of ſugar beeing finely beaten, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding two or three ſpoonefulls of Roſewater, and that will keep your almonds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oiling: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your paſte, is beaten fine, driue it thin with a rowling pin, and ſo lay it on a bottome of wafers, then raiſe vp a little edge on the ſide, &amp; ſo bake it, then yce it with Roſewater and ſugar, then put it into the ouen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and when you ſee your yee is riſen vp and drie, then take it out of the Ouen and garniſh it
<pb facs="tcp:25027:22"/>with pretie conceipts, as birdes &amp; beaſts being caſt out of ſtanding moldes. Sticke long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fits vpright in it, caſt bisket and carowaies in it, and ſo ſerue it; guild it before you ſerue it: you may alſo print of this Marchpane paſte in your molds for banqueting diſhes. And of this paſte our comfit makers at this day make their letters, knots, Armes, eſcocheons, beaſts, birds, &amp; other fancies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> To make biſket bread, otherwiſe called french bisket.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pecke of fine flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, two ounces of Coriander ſeedes, one ounce of annis ſeedes, the whites of foure egges, halfe a pinto of Ale yeaſt, and as much water as will make it vp into ſtiffe paſt, your water muſt be but blood warme, then bake it in a long roll as big as your thigh, let it ſtay in the ouen but one houre, and when
<pb facs="tcp:25027:22"/>it is a daye olde, pare it and ſlice it ouerthwart, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſugar it ouer with fine poudred ſugar, and ſo drie it in an ouen again, and being drye, take it out and ſugar it again, then boxe it, and ſo you may keepe it all the yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> To make prince bisket.</head>
               <p>TAke one pounde of verie fine flower, and one pounde of fine ſugar, and eight egges, and two ſpoonfuls of Roſewater, and one ounce of carroway ſeeds, and beat it all to batter one whole hour, for the more you beat it, the better your bread is, then bake it in cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins of white plate, beeing baſted with a little butter before you put in your batter, and ſo keepe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> To make another kinde of bisket, called biskettello.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe an ounce of gumme Dragagant, diſſolue it in Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa
<pb facs="tcp:25027:23"/>Roſewater with the iuice of a lem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon and two graines of muske, then ſtraine it through a faire lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth with the white of an eg, then take halfe a pound of fine ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar being beaten, and one ounce of carroway ſeedes, beeing alſo beaten and ſearced, and then beat them altogether in a mortar till they come to paſte, then rol them vp in ſmall loaues about the big mall egge, put vnder the of a ſmall egge, put vnder the bottome of euerie one, a peece of a wafer, and ſo bake them in an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon a ſheete of paper, cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the ſides as you do a manchet, and pricke them in the middeſt: when you break them vp, they will bee hollow and full of eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> To make Giagerbread.</head>
               <p>TAke three ſtale manchets and grate them, drie them, and ſift them through a fine ſieue, then
<pb facs="tcp:25027:23"/>ad vnto them one ounce of ginger being beaten, and as much Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, one ounce of liquerice &amp; anniſeedes beeing beaten toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſearced, halfe a pound of ſugar, then boile all theſe together in a poſnet, with a quart of claret wine till they come to a ſtiffe paſte with often ſtirring of it; and when it is ſtiffe, molde it on a table and ſo driue it thin, &amp; print it in your moldes, duſt your moldes with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, and liquerice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mixed together in fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. This is your Ginger bread v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the court, and in all gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes at feſtiuall times. It is otherwiſe called drie Leach.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> To make drie Gingerbread.</head>
               <p>TAke halſe a pound of almonds and as much grated cake, and a pounde of fine ſugar, and the yolke of two newe laid egges, the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:24"/>iuyce of a Lemmon, and 2 graines of muske, beate all theſe together till they come to a paſte, then print it with your molds, and ſo dry it vpon papers in an ouen after your bread is drawne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>24.</hi> To make puſſe paſte.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of the fineſt flower and the whites of three egges, and the yolkes of two, and a little colde water, and ſo make it into perfect paſte, then driue it with a rouling pin abroade, then put on ſmall peeces of butter as big as Nuts vppon it, then folde it ouer, then driue it abroade againe, then put ſmall peeces of butter vpon it as you did before, doe this tenne times, alwaies folding the paſte and putting butter betweene cue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie folde. You may conuey anie prettie forced diſh, as Florentine, Cherry tarte, rice, or pippins, &amp;c. betweene two ſheets of that paſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> To make paſte ſhort without butter.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of fine flower, and put it into a pipken, and bake it in an ouen when you bake man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, then take the yolkes of 2. or three egs, and a pint of creame, &amp; make paſte, put it into two ounces of ſugar beeing ſinely beaten, and ſo you ſhall make your paſte ſhort without butter or ſewet. In like ſort when you make ſugar cakes bake your flower firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> To make cryſtall gelly.</head>
               <p>TAke a knockle of veale, and two calues feete (your calues feete beeing flayed &amp; ſcalded) and boile them in faire ſpring water, and when they are boyled readie to eate, you may ſaue your fleſh &amp; not boyle it to peeces, for if you doe ſo, the gelly will looke thicke, then take a quart of the cleereſt
<pb facs="tcp:25027:25"/>of the ſame broth, and put it into a poſnet, adding thereunto gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, white pepper, 6. whole cloues, one nutmeg quartered, one grain of muske. put all theſe whole ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a little bag, and boyle them in your gelly, ſeaſon, it with ſome ounces of ſugar candie, and three ſpoonefuls of Roſewater, ſo let it run through your gelly bag, and if you meane to haue it ſooke of an amber colour, bruiſe your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and let them boyle in your gelly looſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> To make Leach of Almonds.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pounde of ſweete Almonds, and beate them in a mortar, then ſtraine them with a pinte of ſweete milke from the Cow, then put vnto it one graine of muske, two ſpoonfuls of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, two ounces of fine ſugar, the waight of three whole ſhillings of I ſinglaſſe that is verie white,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:25"/>and ſo boyle them, then let all run through a ſtrainer, then may you ſlice the ſame and ſo ſerue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>28.</hi> To make Quidini of Quinces.</head>
               <p>TAke the kernells out of eight great Quinces, and boyle them in a quarte of ſpring water, till it come to a pinte, then put into it a quarter of a pinte of Roſewater, and one pound of fine ſugar, and ſo let it boyle till you ſee it come to be of a deepe colour: then take a drop, and drop it on the bottom of a ſaweer, and if it ſtand, take it off, then let it run through a gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bagge into a baſon, then ſet on your baſon vpon a chaſing diſh of coales to keepe it warme, then take a ſpoone, and fill your boxes as ful as you pleaſe, and when they bee colde couer them: and if you pleaſe to printe it in moldes, you muſt haue molds made to the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your boxe, and wet your it run into your mold, and when
<pb facs="tcp:25027:26"/>molds with Roſewater, and ſo let it is colde turne it off into your boxes. If you wette your moldes with water, your gelly will fall out of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>29.</hi> To make gelly of strawberies, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, Raſpisberies, or any ſuch tender fruite.</head>
               <p>TAke your beries and grinde them in an Alablaſter mortar with foure ounces of ſugar and a quarter of a pinte of faire water, and as much Roſewater, and ſo boile it in a poſnet with a little peece of Iſinglas, and ſo let it run through a fine cloth into your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes, and ſo you may keepe it all the yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>30.</hi> To make paſte of Genua of Quinces.</head>
               <p>TAke Quinces and pare them, and cut them in ſlices, &amp; bake
<pb facs="tcp:25027:26"/>them in an ouen dry in an earthen pot without any other iuyce then their owne, then take one pound thereof, ſtraine it, and put it into a ſtone mortar with halfe a pounde of ſugar, and when you haue beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it vp to paſte, print it in your molds and dry it three or foure times in an ouen after you haue drawne bread, &amp; when it is throughly drie and hardened, you may boxe it, &amp; it will keepe all the yeere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>31.</hi> To make marmelade of Quinces or Damſons.</head>
               <p>WHen you haue boyled your Quinces or Damſons ſufe ficiently, ſtraine them; then dry the pulpe in a pan on the fire, and when you ſee there is no water in it, but that it beginneth to bee ſtiffe, then mixe two pound of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar with 3. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of pulp, this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melade will be white marmelade: and if you will haue it looke with
<pb facs="tcp:25027:27"/>with an high colour, put your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and your pulpe together, ſo ſoone as your pulpe is drawne, and let them both boile together, and ſo it will looke of the colour of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie marmelade, like vnto a ſtewed warden, but if you dry your pulpe firſt, it will looke white and take leſſe ſugar: you ſhall knowe when it is thicke enough, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a little into a ſawcer, letting it coole before you box it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>32.</hi> To make ſucket of Lettuce ſtalkes.</head>
               <p>TAke Lettuce ſtalkes, and pill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the outſide, then perboile them in faire water, then let them ſtand all night drie, then take halfe a pinte of the ſame liquour; and a quarter of a pinte of Roſewater, and ſo boyle it to ſirrup, and when your ſirup is betwixt hot &amp; cold, put in your aforeſaid rootes, and let them ſtand all night in your ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup to make them take ſugar, and
<pb facs="tcp:25027:27"/>then the next day your ſirup wil be weake againe, then boyle it again, and take out your rootes. In the like ſorte may you keepe Orenge pilles, or greene walnuts, or anie thing that hath the bitternes firſt taken from it, by boyling in water</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>33.</hi> To candie nutmegs or ginger, with an hard rocke candie.</head>
               <p>TAke one pounde of fine ſugar, and eight ſpoonefuls of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and the waight of 6. pence of Gum Arabique, that is cleere, boyle them together to ſuch an height, as that dropingſome ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of out of a ſpoone, the ſirup doe rope and run into the ſmalnes of an haire, then put it into an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pipken, wherein place your nutmegs, ginger, or ſuch like, then ſtop it cloſe with a ſaucer, and lute it well with clay, that no aire may enter, then keep it in a hote place three weekes, and it will candie
<pb facs="tcp:25027:28"/>hard. You muſt break your pot with an hammer, for otherwiſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get out your candie. You may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo candy Orenges, or Lemmons in like ſort if you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> To preſerue Orenges after the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall faſhion.</head>
               <p>TAke Orenges &amp; coare them on the ſide and lay them in water. then boile them in fair water til they betender, ſhift them in the boyling to take away their bitterneſſe, then take ſugar and boyle it to the height of ſirup as much as will couer them, and ſo put your Orenges into it, and that will make them take ſugar. If you haue 24. Orenges, beate 8. of them till they come to paſte with a pouade of fine ſugar, then fill euery one of the other Orenges with the ſame, and ſo boile them again in your ſirup: then there will be marmelade of orenges within your orenges, &amp; it wil cut like an hard egge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>35.</hi> To candie Orenge pilies.</head>
               <p>TAke your Orenge pilles after they be preſerued, then take fine ſugar and Roſewater, &amp; boile it to the height of <hi>Manus Chriſti,</hi> then drawe through your ſugar, then lay them on the bottome of a ſieue, and dry them in an ouen after you haue drawne bread, and they will be candied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>36.</hi> To preſerue Cowcumbers all the yeere.</head>
               <p>TAke a gallon of faire water, &amp; a pottle of veriuice, and a pint of bay ſalt, and a handfull of green fennell or Dill: boyle it a little, and when it is cold put it into a barrel, and then put your Cowcumbers into that pickle, and you ſhal keep them all the yeere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>37.</hi> To preſerue broome capers all the yeare.</head>
               <p>BOyle a quart of Veriuice and an handfull of baye ſalte, and therein you may keepe them all the yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>38.</hi> To colour ſugar plate with ſeuerall colours.</head>
               <p>YOu may mixe Roſet with your fine ſacred ſugar vntill the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour pleaſe you, and ſo ſhall you haue a faire murrey colour. Sap-greene muſt be tempred in a little Roſewater, hauing ſome gumme firſt diſſolued therein, and ſo laye it on with a penſill vpon your paſte in apt places. With ſaffron you may make a yellow colour in the like manner, firſt drying and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering your ſaffron, and after it hath coloured the Roſewater ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientlie, by ſtrayning it through fine linnen. The powder of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:29"/>maketh a walnut colour, and ginger and Cinamon together a lighter colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>39.</hi> To make croſſes for the ſea.</head>
               <p>FIrſt make paſte of ſugar &amp; gum Dragagant mixed together, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mixe therewith a reaſonable qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiry of the powder of Cinamon &amp; ginger, and if you pleaſe a little muske alſo, and make it vpp into rols of ſeuerall faſhions, gilding them heere and there. In the ſame manner you may alſo conuey any purgatiue, vomit, or other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine into ſugar paſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>40.</hi> To make paſte of Violets, Roſes, Marigolds, Cowſlips, or liquerice.</head>
               <p>SHred, or rather powder the dry leaues of your flower, putting thereunto ſome fine powder of Ginger, Cinamon, and a little muske if you pleaſe, mixe them all
<pb facs="tcp:25027:30"/>confuſedly together, then diſſolue ſome ſugar in Roſewater, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing boyled a little, put ſome ſaffron therein, if you worke vpon Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golds, or elſe you may leaue out your ſaffron, boyle it on the fire vnto a ſufficient height, you muſt alſo mixe therewith the pap of a roaſted apple being firſt well dried in a diſhe ouer a chafing diſh of coales, then poure it vpon a tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, beeing firſt ſprinkled ouer with Roſewater, and with a knife worke the paſte together. Then breake ſome ſugar candy ſmall, but not to powder, and with gumme dragagant, faſten it heere and there to make it ſeeme as if it were roch candied, cut the paſte into peeces of what faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you liſt with a knife firſt wet in Roſewater. In licorice paſte you muſt leaue out the pap of the pippin, and then worke your paſte into drie rolles. Remember to ſearce the liquorice through a fine ſearce. Theſe rolles
<pb facs="tcp:25027:30"/>are very good againſt any cough or colde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>41.</hi> To make Marmelade of Lemmons or Orenges.</head>
               <p>TAke ten lemmons or orenges &amp; boyle them with half a doze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pippins, &amp; ſo drawe them throgh a ſtrainer, then take ſo much ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar as the pulp doth wey, &amp; boyle it as you doe Marmelade of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then box it vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>42.</hi> How to candie Nutmegs, Ginger, Mace, &amp; flowers, in halfe a day with hard or roch candie.</head>
               <p>Lay your Nutmegs in ſteepe in common Lee made with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie aſhes 24. houres; take them out and boyle them in faire water till they be tender, and to take out the Lee: then drie them and make a ſirup of double refined ſugar and a little Roſewater to the height
<pb facs="tcp:25027:31"/>of a <hi>manus Chriſti,</hi> place this ſirrup in a gentle balneo, or ſome ſmall heate, putting your Nutmegs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſirup. Note that you muſt skim the ſugar as it caſteth anie skumme, before you put in your Nutmegs, then hauing ſugar can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die firſt bruiſed groſſely, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through colanders of ſeuerall bigneſſe, take the ſmalleſt thereof, and roule your Nutmegs vp and downe therein, either in a diſh or vpon clean paper, then ſtoue your Nutmegges in a cupboard with a chafing diſh of coales, which muſt be made hote of purpoſe before you ſet them in: and when they are drie enough, dip them againe in freſh ſirup boyled to his height as before; and roule them in the groſſer ſugar candie, &amp; then ſtoue them againe till they be hard, and ſo the thirde time if you will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their candie. Note that you muſt ſpend all the ſugar which you diſſolue at one time with can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying
<pb facs="tcp:25027:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>of one thing or other there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in preſently: the ſtronger that your lee is, the better; &amp; the nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, ginger, &amp;c. wouldly in ſteep in the lee, 10, or 12, daies, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſirup of ſugar in a ſtoue or Cupboarde with a chafing diſh and coales one whole weeke, and then you may candie them ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, as before. Flowers and fruits are done preſently without anie ſuch ſteeping or ſtouing as before: onely they muſt bee put into the ſtoue after they are coated with your powdered ſugar candie: and thoſe flowers of fruits as they are ſo dainely done, ſo they will not laſt aboue two or three daies faire, and therefore onely to be prepared for ſome ſet banquet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Casting of ſugar in partie moldes of wood.</head>
               <p>LAy your moldes in faire water three or foure houres before
<pb facs="tcp:25027:32"/>you caſt, then dry vp your inward moiſture with a cloth of Linnen, then boyle roſewater &amp; refined ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar together, but not to anie great ſtiffneſſe, then poure it into your moldes, let your molds ſtand one houre, and then gently part or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the moldes, and take out that which you haue caſt, you may alſo worke the paſte <hi>aniè numero.</hi> 12.13. into theſe molds, firſt printing or preſſing gently a little of the paſte into the one halfe, and after with a knife taking away the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous edges, and ſo likewiſe of the other halfe: then preſſe both ſides of the mold together, two or three times, &amp; after take away the creſt that will ariſe in the middeſt: and to make the ſides to cleaue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you may touch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt ouer with Gum Dragagant diſſolued, before you preſſe the ſides of the mold together: note that you may conuey comfits within, before you cloſe the ſides. You may caſt of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:32"/>any of theſe mixtures or paſtes in alablaſter molds, molded from the life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>44.</hi> To mold of a Lemmon, orenge, peare, Nut. &amp;c. and after to caſt it hollowe within, of ſugar.</head>
               <p>FIll a woodden platter halfe full of ſande, then preſſe downe a Lemmon, peare, &amp;c. therein to the iuſt halfe thereof, then temper ſome burnt Alablaſter with faire water in a ſtone or copper diſh, of the bigneſſe of a great ſiluer boll, and caſt this pap into your ſande, and from thence clap it vppon the Lemmon, Peare, &amp;c. preſſing the pap cloſe vnto it. Then after a while take out this halfe parte with the Lemmon in it, and pare it euen in the inſides as neere as you can, to make it reſemble the iuſt halfe of your Lemmon, then make 2. or 3. litle holes in the halfe (<hi>viz</hi> in the edges therof) laying it downe in the ſande againe, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:25027:33"/>caſte an other halfe vnto it, then cut off a peece of the top of both your partie moldes, &amp; caſt thereto another cap in like manner as you did before. Keep theſe three parts bound together with tape till you haue cauſe to vſe them: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you caſt, lay them alwaies in water, and drie vp the water again before you poure in the ſugar. Coloury our Lemmon with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſaffron ſteeped in Roſewater; vſe your ſugar in this manner: Boile refined or rather double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined ſugar and Roſewater to his full height, <hi>viz.</hi> till by powring ſome out of a ſpoone, it will run at the laſt as fine as a haire; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the cappe of your molde, poure the ſame therein, filling vp the mold aboue the hole, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently clap on the cap, and preſſe it downe vppon the ſugar, then ſwing it vpp and downe in your hande, turning it rounde, and bringing the neather parte ſome
<pb facs="tcp:25027:33"/>times to be the vpper parte in the turning, and <hi>è conuerſo.</hi> This is the manner of vſing an Orenge, Lemmon, or other round molde: but if it be long as a pigs foot will be, beeing molded, then roule it, and turne it vp and downe longe waies in the aire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>45.</hi> How to keepe the drie pulpe of Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Prunes, Damſons &amp;c. all the yeare.</head>
               <p>TAke of thoſe kinde of cherries which are ſharpin taſte (<hi>Quaere</hi> if the common blacke and redde cherrie will not alſo ſerue, hauing in the ende of the decoction a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle oyle of Vitrioll or Sulphur, or ſome veriuice of ſoure grapes, or iuice of Lemmons mixed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, to giue a ſufficient tartneſſe) pull off their ſtalks and boile them by themſelues without the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any liquour in a caldron or pipken, and when they begin
<pb facs="tcp:25027:34"/>once to boile in their owne iuice, ſtir them hard at the bottom with a ſpattle, leaſt they burn to the pans bottom. They haue boyled ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, when they haue caſte off all their skins, and that the pulp and ſubſtance of the cheries is grown to a thicke pap: then take it from the fire, and let it coole, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the ſtones and skins, by paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the pulpe onely through the bottome of a ſtrainer reuerſed as they vſe in <hi>caſſia fiſtula,</hi> then take this pulpe and ſpread it thin vpon glazed ſtones or diſhes, and ſo let it drie in the ſunne, or elſe in an ouen preſently after you haue drawne your breade, then looſe it from the ſtone or diſh, &amp; keepe it to prouoke the appetite, and to coole the ſtomacke in feuers, and all other hote diſeaſes. Proue the ſame in all manner of fruit. If you feare aduſtion in this worke, you may finiſh it in hote balneo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>46.</hi> How to dry all manner of plums or Cheries in the ſunne.</head>
               <p>IF it be a ſmall fruite, you muſt dry them whole, by laying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abroad in the hote ſunne, in ſtone or pewter diſhes, or Iron or braſſe pannes, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them as you ſhall ſee cauſe. But if the plum be of any largeneſſe, ſlit each plum on the one ſide from the top to the bottome, and then lay them abroad in the Sunne: but if they be of the biggeſt ſort, then giue ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plum a ſlit on each ſide: and if the ſun doe not ſhine ſufficiently du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the practice, then dry them in an ouen that is temperately warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>47.</hi> How to keepe apples, peares, quinces, wardens. &amp;c. all the yeare, drie.</head>
               <p>PAre them, take out the coares, and ſlice them in thinne ſlices
<pb facs="tcp:25027:35"/>laying them to drie in the Sunne in ſome ſtone or metalline diſhes, or vpon high frame couered with courſe canuas, now and then tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, and ſo they will keepe all the yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>48.</hi> To make greene Ginger vpon ſirup.</head>
               <p>TAke Ginger one pounde, pare it cleane, ſteepe it in red wine and vinegar equally mixed, let it ſtand ſo 12. dayes in a cloſe veſſell, and euery day once or twice ſtir it vp and downe, then take of wine one gallon, and of vinegar a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, ſeeth altogether to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of a moitie or half, then take a pottle of cleane clarified honey or more, and put thereunto, and let them boile well together, then take halfe an ounce of ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron. finely beaten, and put it thereto with ſome ſugar if you pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>49</hi> To make ſucket of greene Walnuts.</head>
               <p>TAke Walnuts when they are no bigger then the largeſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill nut, pare away the vppermoſt greene, but not too deepe, then ſeeth them in a pottle of water till the water be ſodden away, then take ſo much more of freſh water, and when it is ſodden to the halfe, put thereto a quart of vinegar and a pottle of clarified honie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>50.</hi> To make conſerue of prunes or Damſons.</head>
               <p>TAke ripe Damſons, put them into ſcalding water, let them ſtand a while, then boyle them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the fire till they breake, then ſtraine out the water through a colander, and let them ſtand ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to coole, then ſtraine the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons through the colander, taking
<pb facs="tcp:25027:36"/>away the ſtones and skinnes, then ſet the pulpe ouer the fire againe, and put thereto a good quantitie of red wine, and boile them wel to a ſtiffeneſſe, euer ſtirring them vp and downe, and when they bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſufficiently boyled, put in a conuenient proportion of ſugar, ſtir all well together, and after put it in your gally pots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>51.</hi> To make conſerue of ſtrawberies.</head>
               <p>FIrſt ſeeth them in water, and then caſt away the water, and ſtraine them, then boyle them in white wine, and worke as before in damſons, or elſe ſtraine them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ripe, then boyle them in wine and ſugar till they be ſtiffe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>52.</hi> Conſerue of prunes or Damſons made another way.</head>
               <p>TAke a pottle of damſons, prick them and put them into a pot;
<pb facs="tcp:25027:36"/>putting thereto a pinte of Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or wine, and couer your pot, let them boile well, then incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them by ſtirringe, and when they be tender let them coole, &amp; ſtraine them with the liquor alſo, then take the pulpe and ſet it ouer the fire, and put thereto a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantitie of ſugar, and boile them to their height or conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and put it vp in gally pots, or iarre glaffes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>53.</hi> How to candie Ginger, Nutmegs, or any Roote or flowers.</head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of a pounde of the beſt refined ſugar, or ſugar candie which you can get, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, put thereto two ſpoonfuls of Roſewater, dip therein your Nutmegs, ginger, rootes, &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt ſodden in faire water till they bee ſoft and tender, the oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you dip them in your ſirrup, the thicker the candie will bee,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:37"/>but it will be the longer in candy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: your ſirrup muſt bee of ſuch ſtiffneſſe, as that a droppe thereof beeing let fall vpon a pewter diſh, may congeale and harden being cold. You muſt make your ſirrup in a chafing diſh of coales, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a gentle fire: after your ſirup is once at his full height, then put them vpon papers preſently into a ſtoue, or in diſhes, continue fire ſome ten or twelue dayes, till you finde the candie hard and gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like diamonds; you muſt dip the red roſe, the gillow flower, the marigold, the borrage flower, and all other flowers but once.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The arte of comfetmaking, teaching how to couer all kinds of ſeedes, fruits o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpices with ſugar.</head>
               <p>Firſt of all you muſt haue a deep bottomed baſon of fine cleane braſſe or latton, with two eares of Iron to hang it with two ſeuerall
<pb facs="tcp:25027:37"/>cords ouer a baſon or earthen pan with hote coales.</p>
               <p>You muſt alſo haue a broad pan to put aſhes in, &amp; hote coales vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
               <p>You muſt haue a cleane latton baſon to melt your ſugar in, or a faire braſen skillet.</p>
               <p>You muſt haue a fine braſen ladle, to let run the ſugar vpon the ſeedes.</p>
               <p>You muſt alſo haue a braſen ſlice, to ſcrape away the ſugar fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hanging baſon if neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               <p>Hauing all theſe neceſſarie veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels &amp; inſtruments, worke as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>Chooſe the whiteſt, fineſt, and hardeſt ſugar, and then you need not to clarifie it, but beate it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into fine powder that it may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the ſooner.</p>
               <p>But firſt make all your ſeedes verie cleane, &amp; dry them in your hanging baſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:38"/>Take for euery two pounde of ſugar, a quarter of a pound of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſeedes, or Coriander ſeedes, and your Comfites will be greate enough, and if you wil make them greater, take halfe a pound more of ſugar, or one pound more, and then they will be faire &amp; large.</p>
               <p>And halfe a pounde of Annis ſeeds, with two pound of ſugar wil make fine ſmall comfits.</p>
               <p>You may alſo take a quarter and a halſe of annis ſeedes, and three pound of ſugar, or halfe a pounde of annis ſeedes and foure pounde of ſugar. Do the like in Coriander ſeedes.</p>
               <p>Melt your ſugar in this maner, <hi>viz.</hi> Put three pounds of your powder ſugar into the baſon, and one pinte of cleane running wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereunto, ſtirre it well with a braſen ſlice, vntill all be moiſt and well wet, then ſet it ouer the fire, without ſmoak or flame, and melt it well, that there bee no whole
<pb facs="tcp:25027:38"/>griſtie ſugar in the bottome, and let it ſeeth mildelye, vntill it will ſtreame from the ladle like Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, with a long ſtreame and not drop, then it is come to his decoction, let it ſeeth no more, but keepe it vpon hot imbers that it may run from the ladle vpon the ſeedes.</p>
               <p>To make them ſpeedily. Let your water be ſeething hot, or ſeething &amp; put powder of ſugar vnto the, caſt on your ſugar boyling hote: haue a good warme fire vnder the hanging baſon.</p>
               <p>Take as much water to your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, as will diſſolue the ſame.</p>
               <p>Neuer skim your ſugar if it bee cleane and fine.</p>
               <p>Put no kind of ſtarch or amy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum to your ſugar.</p>
               <p>Seeth not your ſugar too long, for that will make it black, yellow or tawnie.</p>
               <p>Moue the ſeeds in the hanging baſon as faſt as you can or may,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:39"/>when the ſugar is in caſting.</p>
               <p>At the firſt coate put on but one halfe ſpoonfull with the ladle, and all to moue the baſon, moue, ſtirre and rub the ſeedes with thy left hand a pretie while, for they will take ſugar the better, &amp; dry them well after euerie coate.</p>
               <p>Do this at euerie coate, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in mouing the baſon, but alſo with the ſtirring of the comfits with the left hand and drying the ſame: thus dooing you ſhall make great ſpeed in the making: as, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie three houres you may make three pound of comfits.</p>
               <p>And as the comfits do increaſe in greatnes, ſo you may take more ſugar in your ladle to caſt on. But for plaine comfits let your ſugar be of a light decoction laſt, and of a higher decoction firſt, &amp; not too hote.</p>
               <p>For criſpe and ragged comfits, make your ſugar of a high deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, euen as high as it may run
<pb facs="tcp:25027:39"/>from the Ladle, and let fall a foote high or more from the ladle, and the hoter you caſt on your ſugar. the more ragged will your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets be. Alſo the comfets will not take ſo much of the ſugar as they will vpon a light decoction, and they will keepe their raggedneſſe long. This high decoction muſt ſerue for eight or ten coats in the end of the worke, and put on at euerie time but one ſpoonful, and haue a light hand with your baſon, caſting on but little ſugar.</p>
               <p>A quarter of a pounde of Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander ſeeds, and three pounds of ſugar will make greate, huge, and big comfets.</p>
               <p>See that you keepe your ſugar alwaies in good temper in the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that it burne not into lumpes or gobbets: and if your ſugar be at anie time too high boyled, put in a ſpoonfull or two of water, &amp; keepe it warily with the ladle, and let your fire alwaies bee without
<pb facs="tcp:25027:40"/>ſmoake or flame.</p>
               <p>Some commende a ladle that hath a hole in it to let the ſugar run through of a height, but you may make your comfites in their perfect forme and ſhape only with a plaine ladle.</p>
               <p>When your comſites be made, ſet your diſhes with your comfits vppon papers in them before the heat of the fire, or in the hot ſun, or in an Ouen after the bread is drawen, by the ſpace of an houre or two, and this will make them very white.</p>
               <p>Take a quarter of a pounde of Annis ſeedes, and two pound of ſugar, and this proportion will make them verie great, and euen a like quantity take of Carroway ſeede, Fennell ſeede, and Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeede.</p>
               <p>Take of the fineſt Cinamon, and cut it into prettie ſmall ſticks beeing drye, and beware you wette it not, for that deadeth
<pb facs="tcp:25027:40"/>the cinamon, and then worke as in other comfits. Do this with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge rindes likewiſe.</p>
               <p>Worke vpon ginger, cloues, and Almonds, as vpon other ſeeds.</p>
               <p>The ſmaller that Annis ſeede comfits be, the fairer, the harder, and ſo in all other.</p>
               <p>Take the powder of fine Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon two drammes, of fine muske diſſolued in a little water one ſcruple, mingle theſe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the hanging baſon, and caſt them vppon ſugar of a good decoction, then with thy left hand moue it to and fro, and drie it wel, doe this often, vntill they bee as great as poppie ſeeds, and giue in the ende three or foure coates of a light decoction, that they may be round and plaine, &amp; with an high decoction you may make them criſpe.</p>
               <p>You muſt haue a coorſe ſearce made for the purpoſe with haire or with parchment full of holes to
<pb facs="tcp:25027:41"/>part and diuide the comfets into ſeuerall ſorts.</p>
               <p>To make paſte for comfets. Take fine grated breade foure ounces, fine elect Cinamon powdred half an ounce, fine ginger powder one dramme, ſaffron powdred, a little, white ſugar two ounces, &amp; a fewe ſpoonfuls of borrage water, ſeeth the water and the ſugar together, and put to the ſaffron, then firſt mingle the crummes of bread &amp; the ſpices well together, dry the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; put the liquor ſcalding hote, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtuffe, &amp; being hot labour it with thy hand, and make balles or other formes therof, dry them and couer them as comfets.</p>
               <p>Coriander ſeeds two ounces, ſugar one pound and a halfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth very faire comfets.</p>
               <p>Annis ſeeds three ounces, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar halfe a pound, or annis ſeedes two ounces, and ſugar 6. ounces, will make faire comfits.</p>
               <p>Euerie dram of fine Cinamon,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:41"/>will take at the leaſt a pound of ſugar for biskets, and likewiſe of ſugar or ginger powder.</p>
               <p>Halfe an ounce of groſſe Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wil make almoſt three drams of fine powder ſearced, after it is well beaten.</p>
               <p>Sugar powder one ounce will take at the leaſt a pound of ſugar to make your biskets faire.</p>
               <p>Carrowaies will be faire at 12. coates.</p>
               <p>Put into the ſugar a little Amy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum diſſolued for fiue or ſix of the laſt coates, and that will make them exceeding criſpe and if you put too much Amylum or ſtarch to the comfits which you woulde haue criſpe, it will make them flat and ſmooth.</p>
               <p>In anie other confection of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted ſugar mixed with gum Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagant, put no kinde of Amylum: beware of it, for it will make thy worke clammie.</p>
               <p>To make redde comfits, ſeeth 3.
<pb facs="tcp:25027:42"/>or foure ounces of braſell with a little water, take of this red water 4. ſpoonfulls, of ſugar one ounce, and boile it to his decoction, then giue 6. coates and it will bee of a good colour, or elſe you may turn ſo much water with one dramm of turneſole, doing as before.</p>
               <p>To make greene comfits, ſeeth ſugar with the iuice of beets.</p>
               <p>To make them yellow, ſeeth ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron with ſugar.</p>
               <p>In making of comfits, alwaies when the water doth ſeeth, then put in your ſugar powder, and let it ſeeth a little vntill it bee cleane diſſolued and boyled to his per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect decoction, &amp; that the white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the colour be clean gone, and if you let it ſettle, you ſhall ſee the ſugar ſomwhat clear.</p>
               <p>For biskets take two ſpoonfulls of liquor, of ſugar ſearced in a courſe ſearce one dram, and of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar powder to be melt &amp; caſt, one ounce. This donne will make the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:42"/>biskets ſomewhat faire, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what greater then poppie ſeeds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aliter.</hi> Take ſugar powder foure drams, ſugar to caſt foure ounces with liquor ſufficient, lay golde or ſiluer on your comfits.</p>
               <p>Euery dramm of ſugar powder will take an ounce of ſugar to be caſt. 8. drammes make one ounce. To thus much powder, for biskets take half a pound of ſugar to caſt theron.</p>
               <p>Coriander ſeedes a quarter of a pound, ſugar 3. pound, Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeedes halfe a pound, ſugar, 3. drams will make faire comfits.</p>
               <p>For biskets, Annis ſeeds halfe a pound, Fennel ſeeds a quarter of a pound, and ſugar two pound ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth.</p>
               <p>In ſixe or eight of the laſt coats put in two ſpoonefuls of ſugar ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hot to make them criſpe.</p>
               <p>To one pound of ſugar take 9. ounces of water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>55.</hi> To make a cullis as white as ſnowe, and in the nature of gellie.</head>
               <p>Take a cocke, ſcalde, waſh and drawe him cleane, ſeethe it in vvhite vvine or rheniſh vvine, sku<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it cleane, clarifie the broth after it is ſtrayned, then take a pinte of thicke and ſvveete creame, ſtraine that to your clarified broth, and your broth vvill become exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faire and vvhite: then take powdred ginger, fine vvhite ſugar &amp; Roſe vvater, ſeething your cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis vvhen you ſeaſon it, to make it take the colour the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>56.</hi> To make Wafers.</head>
               <p>TAke a pinte of flowr, put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a little creame with two yolkes of egges and a little roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvater, vvith a little ſcarced cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ſugar, vvorke them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and bake the paſte vppon hote Irons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>57.</hi> To make Almond butter.</head>
               <p>BLanch your almonds, &amp; beate them as fine as you can with faire water, 2. or three houres, then ſtraine them through a lynnen cloth, boyle them with Roſewater whole mace and annis ſeedes, till the ſubſtance be thicke, ſpreade it vpon a faire cloth, dreining the whey from it, after let it hang in the ſame cloth ſome fewe houres, then ſtraine it and ſeaſon it with Roſewater and ſugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>58, A</hi> white gelly of Almonds.</head>
               <p>TAke Roſewater, gum Draga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant diſſolued, or Iſinglaſſe diſſolued, and ſome Cinamon groſſely beaten, feethe them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then take a pounde of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, blanch and beate them fine with a little faire water, drie them in a faire cloth; and put
<pb facs="tcp:25027:44"/>your water aforeſaid into the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, ſeeth them together and ſtir them continually, then take them, from the fire, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all is boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a ſufficient height.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>59.</hi> To make Leach.</head>
               <p>SEeth a pinte of Creame, and in the ſeething put in ſome diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Iſinglas, ſtirring it vntil it be very thicke, then take a handfull of blanched Almonds, beat them and put them in a diſh with your Creame, ſeaſoning them with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and after ſlice it and diſh it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>60.</hi> Sweete Cakes without eyther ſpice or ſuga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <p>SCrape or waſhe your Parſneps cleane, ſlice them thinne, drie them vpon. Canuas or networke frames, beat them to powder mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one thirde thereof with two
<pb facs="tcp:25027:44"/>thirds of fine wheat flower, make vp your paſte into coates, and you ſhall finde them very ſweete and delicate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>61.</hi> Roſes and Gilloflowres kept long.</head>
               <p>COuer a Roſe that is freſh, and in the bud, and gathered in a faire day after the dewe is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with the whites of egges well beaten, &amp; preſently ſtrew theron the fine powder of ſcarced ſugar, and put them vp in luted pots, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the pots in a coole place in ſand or grauell. With a fillip at any time you may ſhake off this incloſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>62.</hi> Grapes growing all the yeare.</head>
               <p>PVt a Vine ſtalke through a Basket of earth in December, which is likely to be are Grapes,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:45"/>that yeare, and when the Grapes are ripe, cut off the ſtalk vnder the basket (for by this time it hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken roote) keepe the basket in a warme place, and the grapes will continue freſh and faire a long time vpon the vine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>63.</hi> How to drie Roſe leaues, or any other ſingle fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer without wrinkling.</head>
               <p>IF you would performe the ſame well in roſe leaues, you muſt in roſe time make choiſe of ſuch roſes as are neither in the bud, nor full blown (for theſe haue the ſmotheſt leaues of al other) which you muſt eſpecially cull &amp; chooſe from the reſt. Then take right Callis ſand, waſh it in ſome cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of waters, and drie it throughly well, either in an ouen, or in the ſunne; and hauing ſhallow, ſquare or long boxes of 4.5. or 6. inches deepe, make firſt an euen lay of ſande in the bottome, vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:45"/>which lay your roſe leaues one by one (ſo as none of them touch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) till you haue couered all the ſand, then ſtrowe ſand vpon thoſe leaues till you haue thinly coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them all, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make another lay of leaues as before, and ſo lay vpon lay, &amp;c. Set this box in ſome warme place in a hot ſunnie day, (and commonly in two hot ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie dayes they will bee through drie) then take them out carefully with your hand without breaking. Keepe thefe leaues in Iarre glaſſes bound about with paper neere a chimney, or ſtoue, for feare of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting. I finde the red roſe leafe beſt to be kept in this manner; alſo take awaye the ſtalkes of panſies, ſtocke gilloflowers, or other ſingle flowers, pricke them one by one in ſande, presſing downe their leaues ſmooth with more ſande layde eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vpon them. And thus you may haue Roſe leaues, and other flowers to lay about your
<pb facs="tcp:25027:46"/>baſons, windows, &amp;c. all the winter long. Alſo this ſecret is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for a good ſimplifier, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he may drie the leafe of any hearbe in this manner, and lay it being drie in his Herball with the ſimple which it repreſenteth, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by hee may eaſily learne to knowe the names of all ſimples which he deſireth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>64.</hi> Cluſters of Grapes kept till Eaſter.</head>
               <p>CLuſters of grapes hanging vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lines within a cloſe preſſe will laſt till Eaſter, if they ſhrinke you may plumpe them vpp with a little warme water before you eat them. Some vſe to dip the endes of the ſtalkes firſt in pitch: ſome cut a branch of the vine with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cluſter, placing an apple at each end of the branch, now and then renewinge thoſe Apples as they rot, and after hanging them within a preſſe or cupbord, which
<pb facs="tcp:25027:46"/>would ſtand in ſuch a roome (as I ſuppoſe) where the grapes might not freez: for otherwiſe you muſt be forced now and then to make a gentle fire in the room, or elſe the grapes will rot and periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>65.</hi> How to keepe Walnuts a long time plumpe and freſh.</head>
               <p>MAke a laye of the drie ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of crabs when the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice is preſſed from them, couer that lay with Walnuts, and vpon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> make another lay of ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, and ſo one lay vppon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till your veſſell be full where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you meane to keepe them. The Nuts thus kept will pill as if they were new gathered from the tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>66.</hi> An excellent conceit vpon the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of drie Walnuts.</head>
               <p>GAther not your walnuts before they be ful ripe, keep the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with
<pb facs="tcp:25027:47"/>out anie Art vntill Newyeers tide, then breake the ſhels carefully, ſo as you deface not the kernels (&amp; therefore you muſt make choiſe of ſuch nuts as haue thinne ſhels) whatſoeuer you finde to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way eaſilie, remoue it: ſtiepe theſe kernels in conduit water, fortie eight houres, then will they ſwell and grow verie plumpe and faire, and you may pill them eaſily, and preſent them to any friende you haue for a Newyeares gift: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pilled, they muſt bee eaten within two or three houres, or els they loſe their whitenes &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but vnpilled they will laſt 2. or 3. dayes faire and freſh. This of a kind Gentlewoman, whoſe skill I doe highly commend, and whoſe caſe I doe greatlie pitie; ſuch are the hard fortunes of the beſt wits and natures in our dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>67.</hi> How to keepe Quinces in a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent maner.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:47"/>
               <p>MAke choiſe of ſuch as are ſound, &amp; gathered in a faire, drie and ſunny day, place them in a veſſell of wood, containing a firkin or thereabout, then couer them with peny ale, and ſo let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſt: and if the liquor carrie anie bad ſcum, after a day or two take it off, euerie 10. or 12. dayes let out your peny ale at a hole in the bottome of your veſſell, ſtop the hole and fill it vp again with freſh peny ale, you may haue as much for two pence at a time as will ſerue for this purpoſe, theſe Quin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces being baked at Whitſontide did taſte more daintily then any of thoſe which are kept in our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall decoctions or pickels.</p>
               <p>Alſo if you take white wine lees that are neat (but then I feare you muſt get them of the Marchant, for our Tauernes doe hardly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord anie) you may keepe your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Quinces in them verie faire and freſh all the yeare, &amp; therein may
<pb facs="tcp:25027:48"/>you alſo keep your barberies both full and faire coloured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>68</hi> Keeping of Pomegraenats.</head>
               <p>Make choiſe of ſuch Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates as are ſound and not prickt as they tearme it, lap them ouer, thinly with wax, hang them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nailes, where they may touch nothing, in ſome cupbord or clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet in your bedchamber, wher you keep a continual fire, and euery 3. or 4. daies turn the vnderſides vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt, &amp; therefore you muſt ſo hang them in packthred, that they may haue a bowe knot at either end. This way Pomgranates haue beene kept freſh till whitſontide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>69.</hi> Preſeruing of Artichocks.</head>
               <p>CVt off the ſtalkes of your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichokes within two inches of the Apple, and of all the reſt of the ſtalkes make a ſtrong decoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb facs="tcp:25027:48"/>ſlicing them into thinne and ſmall peeces, and keepe them in this decoction: when you ſpende them you muſt lay them firſt in warme water, and then in colde, to take away the bitternes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This of M. <hi>Parſons,</hi> that honeſt and painefull practicer in his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>In a mild &amp; warm winter about a moneth or three weekes before Chriſtmas, I cauſed great ſtore of Artichokes to bee gathered with their ſtalkes in their full length as they grewe, and making firſt a good thicke lay of Artichoke leaues in the bottome of a great and large veſſell I placed my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichokes one vppon another as cloſe as I could touch them, co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer of a pritty thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with Artichoke leaues: theſe Artichokes were ſerued in at my table all the Lent after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the apples being red &amp; ſound, only the tops of the leaues a little vaded, which
<pb facs="tcp:25027:49"/>I did cut away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>70.</hi> Fruit preſerued in pitch.</head>
               <p>DWayberries that do ſomwhat reſemble blacke cherries, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Latine by the name of <hi>Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num laethale,</hi> beeing dipped in mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten pitch, being almoſt cold, and before it congeale and harden a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo hung vp by their ſtalkes, will laſt a whole yeare <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum per</hi> M. <hi>Parſons,</hi> the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie. Prooue what other fruites will alſo bee preſerued in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>71.</hi> To make Cloue or Cinamon ſugar.</head>
               <p>LAy pieces of Sugar in cloſe boxes amongſt ſtickes of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, cloues, &amp;c. and in a ſhort time it will purchaſe both the taſte and ſent of the ſpice. <hi>Probat.</hi> in cloues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>72.</hi> Haſell Nuts kept long.</head>
               <p>A Man of great yeares &amp; expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience aſſured mee, that Nuts may be kept a long time with full kernels, by burying them in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pots well ſtopt, a foot or two in the ground: they keepe beſt in grauelly or ſandy places. But theſe nuts I am ſure wil yeeld no oile as other nuts will, that waxe drie in the ſhels with long keeping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>73.</hi> Cheſnuts kept all the yeare.</head>
               <p>AFter the bread is drawne, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe your Nuts thinly ouer the bottome of the Ouen, and by this meanes the moiſture beeing dryed vp, the Nuts will laſt all the yeare: if at any time you perceiue them to relent, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into your Ouen againe as before.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:50"/>
            <head>Secrets in Diſtillation.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> How to make true ſpirit of wine.</head>
               <p>TAke the fineſt Paper you can get, or elſe ſome Virgine parchment, ſtrayne it verie right and ſtiffe ouer the glaſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wherein you put your ſacke, malmſie or muskadine, oyle the paper or virgin parchment with a penſil moiſtned in the oile of Ben, and diſtill it in the Balneo with a gentle fire, and by this means you ſhall purchaſe only the true ſpirit of wine. You ſhall not haue aboue two or three ounces at the moſte out of a gallon of wine, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth in the forme of a cloude, without any dewe or veins in the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:50"/>helme, lute all the ioyntes well in this diſtillation. This ſpirit will vaniſh in the ayre, if the glaſſe ſtand open.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> How to make the ordinarie ſpirit of wine that is ſolde for <hi>5.</hi> ſhillings, &amp; a noble, a pinte.</head>
               <p>PVt ſacke, malmeſie, or muska<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine into a glaſſe bodie, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one thirde or more of your glaſse empty, ſet it in balneo, or in a pan of aſhes, keeping a ſofte and gentle fire, drawe no longer then till all or moſt part wil burne away, which you may proue nowe and then, by ſetting a ſpoonefull thereof on fire with a paper as it droppeth from the noſe or pipe of the helme, and if your ſpirit thus drawn haue any phlegme therin, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rectify or rediſtil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit again in a leſser body, or in a bolt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ſted of an other body, luting a ſmall head on the top of the ſteel
<pb facs="tcp:25027:51"/>thereof, and ſo you ſhall haue a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtrong ſpirit, or elſe for more expedition, diſtill fiue or ſixe gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons of wine by a Limbecke, and that ſpirit which aſcendeth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, rediſtil in glaſſe as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Spirits of Spices.</head>
               <p>DIſtill with a gentle heat either in balneo, or aſhes, the ſtrong and ſweete water, wherewith you haue drawen oile of cloues, mace, nutmegs, Iuniper, Roſemarie, &amp;c. after it hath ſtoode one moneth cloſe ſtopt, and ſo you ſhall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a moſt delicate Spirite of each of the ſaide aromaticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Spirit of wine taſting of what vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table you pleaſe.</head>
               <p>MAcerate Roſemarie, Sage, ſweet fennell ſeedes, Marie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon or Orenge pils, &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:25027:51"/>in ſpirit of wine a day or two, and then diſtill it ouer againe, vnleſſe you had rather haue it in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per colour: for ſo you ſhall haue it vpon the firſt infuſion without a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny farther diſtillation, and ſome young Alchimiſts doe holde theſe for the true ſpirits of vegetables.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> How to make the water which is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called Balmewater.</head>
               <p>TO euery gallon of claret wine put one pound of green balm Keep that which commeth firſt &amp;. is cleareſt, by it ſelfe: and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond &amp; whiter ſort which is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, and commeth laſt, by it ſelfe, diſtill in a pewter limbeeke luted with paſte to a braſſe pot. Drawe this in May or Iune whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the herb is in his prime.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Roſa-ſolis.</head>
               <p>TAke of the hearbe Roſa-ſolis, gathered in Iuly one gallon,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:52"/>pick out all the black moats from the leaues, dates halfe a pounde, Cinamon, Ginger, cloues, of each one ounce, graines half an ounce, fine ſugar a pound and a halfe, red roſe leaues, greene or dryed foure handfuls, ſteepe all theſe in a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of good Aqua Compoſita in a glaſse cloſe ſtopped with waxe, during twentie daies, ſhake it wel together once euerie two daies. Your ſugar muſt be powdred, your ſpices bruſed onely, or groſſelie beaten, your dates cut in long ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſtones taken awaie. If you adde two or three graines of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber greece, and as much muske in your glaſſe amongſt the reſt of the ingredientes, it will haue a pleaſant ſmel. Some adde the gum amber with coral and pearl finely poudred, and fine leafe golde. Some vſe to boyle Ferdinando bucke in Roſewater, till they haue purchaſed a faire deepe crimſon colour, and when the ſame is cold,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:52"/>they colour their Roſa-ſolis and Aqua Rube a therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Aqua Rubea.</head>
               <p>Take of muske ſixe graines, of Cinamon and ginger of each one ounce, white ſugar candy one pounde, pouder the ſugar, and bruſe the ſpices groſſely, binde them vp in a cleane linnen cloth, and put them to infuſe in a gallon of Aqua co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſita in glaſſe cloſe ſtopped twentie foure houres, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them togither diuers times, then put thereto of turneſole one dram, ſuffer it to ſtand one houre, and then ſhake al together, then if the colour like you after it is ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, poure the cleereſt forth into an other glaſſe: but if you wil haue it deeper coloured, ſuffer it to worke longer vppon the turne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:53"/>
               <head>8. Steeuens <hi>Aqua compoſita.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a gallo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gaſcoign wine, of ginger, galingale, cinamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nutmegs &amp; graines, Annis ſeeds, fennel ſeeds, and carroway ſeeds, of each a dram, of Sage, mints, red Roſes, Time, Pellitorie, Roſemary, wild thime, camomil, lauender, of each a handfull, braie the ſpices ſmall, and bruiſe the herbs, letting them macerate 12. houres, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it now and then, then diſtill by a limbecke of pewter, keeping the firſt cleare water that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by it ſelf, &amp; ſo likewiſe the ſecond. You ſhal draw much about a pinte of the better ſort from euery gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Vſquebath, or Iriſh aqua vitae.</head>
               <p>TO euery gallon of good Aqua compoſita, put two ounces of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:53"/>choſen liquerice bruiſed, and cut into ſmall peeces, but firſt clenſed from all his filth, and two ounces of Annis ſeeds that are cleane &amp; bruiſed, let them macerate fiue or ſixe daies in a wodden Veſſel, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the ſame cloſe, and then draw off as much as will runne cleere, diſſoluing in that cleare Aqua vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae fiue or ſix ſpoonfuls of the beſt Malaſſoes you can get, Spaniſh cute if you can get it, is thought better then Malaſſoes, then put this into another veſſell; and after three or foure daies (the more the better) when the liquor hath fined it ſelf, you may vſe the ſame: ſome adde Dates &amp; Raiſons of the ſun to this receipt; thoſe groundes which remaine you may rediſtill and make more Aqua compoſita of them, &amp; of that Aqua co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſita you may make more Vſque bath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Cinamon-water.</head>
               <p>HAuing a Copper bodie or braſſe pot that will holde 12. gallons, you may well make 2. or 3. gallons of Cinamon water at once. Put into your body ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night 6. gallons of conduit water, and two gallons of ſpirit of wine, or to ſaue charge two gallons of ſpirit drawne from wine lees, Ale, or lowe wine, or ſixe pound of the beſt and largeſt Cinamon you can get, or elſe eight pound of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſort wel bruſed, but not bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into pouder: lute your Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, &amp; begin with a good fire of wood &amp; coals, till the veſſel begin to diſtil, then moderate your fire, ſo as your pipe may drop apace, and run trickling into the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but not blow at anie time: it helpeth much heerein to keep the water in the bucket, not too hot. by often change thereof, it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:25027:54"/>neuer be ſo hot but that you may well indure your finger therein. Then diuide into quart Glaſses the ſpirit vvhich firſt aſcendeth, and vvherein you finde either no taſte or a very ſmall taſte of the Cynamon, then may you boldely after the ſpirit once beginneth to come ſtrong of the cinamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, draw vntill you haue gotten at the leaſt a Gallon in the receiuer, and then diuide often by halfe pintes and quarters of pintes, leaſt you drawe too long: which you ſhall knowe by the faynte taſte and milky coulour which diſtilleth in the ende: this you muſt nowe and then taſte in a ſpoone. Now, when you haue drawen ſo much as you finde good, you may adde thereunto ſo much of your ſpirit that came before your Cinamon water, as the ſame will well beare: which you muſt find by your taſte. But if your ſpirit and your Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be both good, you may of the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:55"/>aforeſaid proportion wil make vp two gallons, or two gallons and a quarte of good Cinamon water. Heere note that it is not amiſſe to obſerue which glaſſe was firſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Spirit that aſcended, and ſo of the ſecond, thirde, and fourth: and when you mix, begin with the laſt glaſſe firſt, &amp; ſo with the next, becauſe thoſe haue more taſte of the Cinamon then that which came firſt, and there fore more fit to bee mixed with your Cinamon water. And if you meane to make but 8. or 9 pintes at once, then begin but with the halfe of this proportion. Alſo that ſpirit which remaineth vnmixed doth ſerue to make Cinamon wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſecond time. This way I haue often proued &amp; found moſt excellent: take heede that your Limbecke be cleane and haue no maner of ſent in it, but of wine or Cinamon, and ſo likewiſe of the glaſſes, ſunnelles and pots which
<pb facs="tcp:25027:55"/>you ſhall vſe about this worke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> How to diſtill Iſop, thime, lauender, Roſemary, &amp;c. after a new and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner.</head>
               <p>HAuing a large Pot containing 12. or 14 gallons, with a Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke to it, or elſe a copper body with a ſerpentine of 20 or 24. gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, and a copper heade, beeing ſuch a veſſell as is commonly vſed in the drawing of Aqua vitae, fill two partes thereof with faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, and one other thirde part with ſuch hearbes as you woulde diſtill, the hearbes being eyther moiſt or drie it skilleth not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whether, let the hearbes mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate all night, and in the morning begin your fire, then diſtil as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Cinamon water, beeing carefull to giue change of waters to your colour alwaies as it nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: drawe no longer then you feele a ſtrong and ſenſible taſte of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:56"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearb which you diſtill, alwayes diuiding the ſtronger from the weaker, and by this meanes you ſhall purchaſe a water farre excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any that is drawen by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pewter ſtill: you may alſo ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the oyle of each hearb which you ſhall finde fleeting on the top or ſummity of your water. This courſe agreeth beſt with ſuch herbs as are not in taſte, and will yeeld their oile by diſtillation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>12</hi> How to make the ſalt of hearbs.</head>
               <p>BVrne whole bundles of dryed Roſemary, Sage, Iſop,  in a cleane ouen, and when you haue gathered good ſtore of the aſhes of the hearb, infuſe warme water vpon them, making a ſtrong and ſharpe Lee of thoſe aſhes, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaporate that Lee, &amp; the reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or ſetling which you finde in the botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, is the ſalt which you ſeek for. Some vſe to filter this lee
<pb facs="tcp:25027:56"/>diuers times before euaporation, that their ſalt may be the clearer and more tranſpare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. This ſalt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of the hearb hath great effects in phyſicke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Spirit of hony.</head>
               <p>PVt one part of honey to 5. parts of water, when the water boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, diſsolue your honey therein, skimme it, and hauing ſodden an houre or two, put it into a wodden veſsell, and when it is but bloud warme, ſet it on worke with yeaſte after the vſuall manner of Beere and Ale, tun it, and when it hath lyen ſome time, it will yeelde his ſpirit by diſtillation; as wine, beer and ale will do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> To diſtil Roſewater at Michaelmas and to haue a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d yeeld as at any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time of the yeare.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:57"/>
               <p>IN the pulling of your Roſes, firſt diuide all the blaſted leaues, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the other freſh leaues, and lay them abroad vpon your table or windowes with ſome cleane linnen vnder them, let them ly 3. or foure houres, or if they bee dewy vntil the dewe be fully vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, put theſe roſe leaues in great ſtone pottes, hauing narrowe mouthes, and well leaded within, (ſuch as the Goldfiners call their hookers, &amp; ſerue to receiue their Aqua fortis, bee the beſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that I know) and when they are well filled, ſtop their mouthes with good corkes, eyther coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all ouer with waxe or molten brimſtone, and then ſet your pot in ſome coole place, and they wil keepe a long time good, and you may diſtill them at your beſt lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. This waie you may diſtill Roſewater good cheape, if you buy ſtore of Roſes, when you find a glutte of them in the market,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:57"/>wherby, they are ſolde for 7. pence or 8. pence the buſhell, you then engroſſe the flower. And ſome hold opinion, that if in the midſt of theſe leaues you put ſome bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken leauen, and after fill vp the pot with Roſe leaues to the top, that ſo in your diſtillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them you ſhal haue a perfect Roſe vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar without the addition of anie common vinegar. I haue knowen Refeleaues kept well in Rondlets, that haue been firſt well ſeaſoned with ſome hote liquor and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues boiled togither, and the ſame pitched ouer on the out ſide, ſo as no aire might penetrate or pearce the veſſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> A ſpeedy diſtillation of Roſewater.</head>
               <p>STampe the leaues, and firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill the iuice being expreſſed, and after diſtil the leaues, and ſo you ſhall diſpatch more with one Stil, then others do with three or
<pb facs="tcp:25027:58"/>foure ſtils. And this water is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie way as medicinable as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeruing in all ſirrups, decoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. ſufficiently, but not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſo pleaſing in ſmell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> How to diſtill wine vinegar or good Aligar, that it may bee both clear &amp; ſharpe.</head>
               <p>I Knowe it is an vſuall manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Nouices of our time to put a quart or two of good vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar into an ordinary leade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill, and ſo to diſtill it as they do all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waters. But this way I do vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diſlike, both for that heere is no ſeperation made at all, and alſo becauſe I feare that the Vinegar doth cary an ill touch with it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaden botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter head or both. And therefore I coulde wiſh rather that the ſame were diſtilled in a large bodie of glaſſe with a head or receiuer, the ſame being placed in ſande or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes.
<pb facs="tcp:25027:58"/>Note that the beſt part of the vinegar is the middle part that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth, for the firſt is fainte and phlegmatick, and the laſt wil taſte of aduſtion, becauſe it groweth heauie toward the latter end, and muſt be vrged vp with a great fire, and therefore you muſt nowe and then taſte of that which commeth both in the beginning &amp; towards the latter end, that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the beſt by it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> How to draw the true ſpirit of reſes, and ſo of all other hearbs and flowers.</head>
               <p>MAcerate the Roſe in his own iuice, adding thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perately warm, a conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proportion either of yeaſt or fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a few daies in fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, till they haue gotten a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; heady ſmel, beginning to incline toward vinegar, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtill them in balneo in glaſs bodies lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their helms (happily a lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke
<pb facs="tcp:25027:59"/>wil do better and rid faſter) and drawe ſo long as you find any ſent of the Roſe to come, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtill you haue purchaſed a perfect ſpirit of the Roſe. You may alſo ferment the iuice of Roſes onelie, and after diſtill the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> An excellent Roſewater.</head>
               <p>VPon the top of your glaſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſtraine a haire cloth, and vpon that lay good ſtore of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues, either drie, or halfe drie, and ſo your water will aſcend ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good both in ſmell and in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. Diſtill either in balneo, or in a gentle fire in aſhes, you may rei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terate the ſame water vppon freſh leaues. This may alſo be done in a leaden Still, ouer which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the breadth you may place more leaues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> An excellent wvy to make the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of all Vegetables.</head>
               <p>EXpreſſe a good quantity of the iuice thereof, ſet it on the fire, and giue it onely a walme or two, then it will grow cleere: before it be cooled, pour away the cleereſt, filter with a peece of cotton, and then euaporate your filtred iuyce, till it come to a thicke ſubſtance, and thus you ſhal haue a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent extracte of the Roſe, Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loflower, &amp;c. with the perfect ſent and taſte of the flower, whereas the common waie is to make the extracte eyther by ſpirit of wine faire water, the water of the plant, or ſome kind of menſtruum.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> To make a water ſmelling of the Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantine, Gilloflowers, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>DRie the hearbe or flower, and diſtill the ſame in faire water
<pb facs="tcp:25027:60"/>in a limbecke, draw no longer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you find ſent in the water that iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth, reiterate that water vpon freſh herbes, and diſtil as before, diuiding the ſweeteſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>21. A</hi> Scottiſh hand water.</head>
               <p>PVt thyme, Lauender, and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary confuſedly together, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make a lay of thicke wine Lees in the bottom of a ſtone pot, vppon which make an other laye of the ſaid hearbes, &amp; then a lay of Lees, and ſo forwarde, lute the pot wel, bury it in the ground for 6. weeks diſtill it, &amp; it is called Dames wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Scotland. A little therof put into a baſon of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon water ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth very ſweet waſhing water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> How to draw the bloud of hearbes.</head>
               <p>STampe the hearb, put the ſame into a large glaſſe, leauing two parts emptie (ſome commend the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:60"/>iuice of the hearbe onely) nip or elſe lute the glaſſe very wel, digeſt it in balneo. 15. or 16. daies, and you ſhall finde the ſame very red, diuide the watriſh part, and that which remaineth is the bloud or eſſence of the hearb.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Roſewater, and yet the Roſeleaues not diſcoloured.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt diſtill in balneo, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottom of your pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Still is through hotte, put in a fewe leaues at once and diſtill them: watch your Still carefully, and as ſoone as thoſe are diſtilled put in more. I know not whether your profit will requite your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, yet accept of it as a newe concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>24.</hi> How to recouer Roſewater, or any other diſtilled water that hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a mother, and is in daunger to be muſty.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:61"/>
               <p>INfuſe your water vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> freſh Roſe leaues, or vpon Roſe cakes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all in peeces, and then after maceration for three or foure houres with a gentle fire, rediſtill your water. Do this in a Limbeck, take heed of drawing too long for burning, vnleſſe your Limbecke ſtand in balneo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> To drawe both good Roſewater, and oyle of Roſes together.</head>
               <p>AFter you haue digeſted your Roſe leaues by the ſpeace of 3. moneths, <hi>ſicut ante, num.</hi> 13. eyther in barrels or hookers, then diſtill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with faire water in a limbeck, draw ſo long as you finde anie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſmell of the Roſe, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the fatty oile that fleeteth on the top of the Roſe water, and ſo you haue both excellent oile of Roſes, and alſo good Roſewater togither, and you ſhall alſo haue more water then by the ordinarie
<pb facs="tcp:25027:61"/>way, and this Roſewater exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth farther in phyſicall compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the other ſerueth beſt for perfumes and caſting bottles. You may alſo diſtill the oyle of <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>num Rhodtum</hi> this way, ſauing that you ſhall not neede to mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the ſame aboue 24 houres in your water or menſtruum before you diſtill: this oyle hath a moſt pleaſing ſmell in a manner equall with the oyle of Roſes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:62"/>
            <head>COOKERIE AND Huſwiferie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>1. To</hi> ſouſe a yong Pig.</head>
               <p>TAke a young Pigge being ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, boile it in faire water and white wine, put therto ſome Baye leaues, ſome whole Ginger, and ſome Nutmegs quartered, a fewe whole cloues, boyle it throughly, and leaue it in the ſame broath in an earthen pot.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>2. <hi>Aliter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a Pig beeing ſcalded, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler him vppe like brawne, and lap your collers in faire cloathes: when the fleſh is boyled tender,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:62"/>take it out, and put it in colde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſalt, and that wil make the skin white, make ſowſing drinke for it, with a quart of white wine, and a pottle of the ſame broth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>3</hi> To boyle a flounder or Pickerel, of the French faſhion.</head>
               <p>TAke a pinte of white wine, the tops of young time and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, a little whole mace, a little whole pepper ſeaſoned with Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice, ſalt, and a peece of ſweete butter, and ſo ſerue it: this broth will ſerue to boyle Fiſh twiſe or thriſe in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> To boile Sparrowes or Larks.</head>
               <p>TAke two ladles full of mutton broth, a little whole mace, put into it a peece of ſweet butter a handful of Parſly being picked, ſeaſon it with ſugar, veriuice, and a little pepper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> To boyle a Capon in white broth.</head>
               <p>BOyle your Capon by it ſelfe in faire water, then take a ladle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or two of mutton broth and a little white wine, a little whole mace, a bundle of ſweete hearbs, a little marrowe, thicken it with Almonds, ſeaſon it with ſugar, and a little veriuyce, boyle a fewe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans by themſelues, and a Date quartered, leaſt you diſcolor your broth, and put it on the breaſt of your Capon, Chicken or Rabbet: if you haue no Almonds, thicken it with Creame, or with yolkes of egges, garniſh your diſhes on the ſides with a Lemmon ſliced &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> To boyle a Mallard, Teale, or Wigin.</head>
               <p>TAke mutton broth, and put it into a pipken, put into the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:63"/>belly of the foule a fevve ſweete hearbes and a little Mace, ſticke halfe a dozen of Cloues in his breaſt, thicken it with a tofte of bread ſtieped in veriuice, ſeaſon it with a little pepper, and a little Sugar, alſo one Onion minced ſmall is very good in the broth of any water foule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> To boyle a legge of Mutton after the French faſhion.</head>
               <p>TAke al the fleſh out of your leg of mutton, or at the but end, preſeruing the skinne whole, and mince it ſmall with Oxe ſuet, and marrow, then take grated bread, ſweete Creame, and yolkes of egges, and a fewe ſweete hearbes, put vnto it Currans, and Raiſins of the ſunne, ſeaſon it with Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, Mace, Pepper, and a little ſugar, &amp; ſo put it into the leg of Mutton againe where you tooke it out, and ſtew it in a pot with a
<pb facs="tcp:25027:64"/>marrow bone or two, ſerue-in the marrowe bones with the ſtewed-broath and fruite, and ſerue-in your legge of mutton drye with carot rootes ſliced, &amp; caſt groſſe pepper vpon the rootes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> To boyle Pigs petitoes on the French faſhion.</head>
               <p>BOyle them and ſlice them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt rolled in a little batter. your batter being made with the yolke of an egge, two ſpoonefuls of ſweete creame, and one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of flower, make ſawce for it with Nutmeg, vinegar and ſugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>9</hi> To boyle Pigeons with rice.</head>
               <p>BOyle them in mutton broath, putting ſweete hearbes in their bellies, then take a little Rice and boyle it in Creame, with a little whole mace, ſeaſon it with ſugar,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:64"/>lay it thick on their breaſts, wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging alſo the iuice of a Lemmon vpon them, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> To boyle a chine of veale, or a chicken in ſharpe broth with hearbes.</head>
               <p>TAke a little mutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> broth, white wine and veriuyce, and a little whole mace, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take lettuce, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and Parſley, and bruiſe it, &amp; put it into your broth, ſeaſoning it with veriuice, pepper and a little ſugar, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> To make Beaumanger.</head>
               <p>TAke the brawne of a Capon, toaſe it like wool, then boile it in ſweete Creame with the whites of two egges, and beeing well boyled, hang it in a cloth, and let the whey run from it, then grinde it in an Alablaſter mortar with a woodden peſteell, then drawe it thorough a thinne Strayner
<pb facs="tcp:25027:65"/>with the yolks of two eggas, and a little Roſewater, then ſet it on a chafing diſh with coales, mixing foure ounces of ſugar with it, and when it is cold diſh it vp like Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond butter, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> To make a Polonian ſawſedge.</head>
               <p>TAke the fillets of an hog, chop them verie ſmall with a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of red ſage, ſeaſon it hot with Ginger and pepper, and then put it into a great ſheepes gut, then let it lie three nights in brine, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boyle it and hang it vp in a chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney where fire is vſually kept, and theſe ſawſedges will laſt one whole yeare. They are good for ſallades, or to garniſh boyled meates, or to make one reliſh a cup of wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> To make tender and delicate Brawne.</head>
               <p>PVt collars of brawne in kettles of water or other apt veſſels, into an ouen heated as you would for houſhold bread, couer the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, &amp; ſo leaue them as long in the ouen as you would doe a batch of bread. A late experience amongſt glentlewomen farre excelling the olde manner of boyling brawné in great &amp; huge kettles. <hi>Quaere</hi> if put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your liquor hot into the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and the brawne a little boiled firſt, if by this meanes you ſhal not giue greate expedition to your worke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Paſte made of fiſh.</head>
               <p>INcorporate the bodie of ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, Stock fiſh, Ling, or any freſh fiſh that is not full of bones, with crums of bread, flower, Iſing laſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:66"/>&amp;c. and with proper ſpices agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the nature of euerie ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall fiſh, and of that paſte molde off the ſhapes &amp; forms of little fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes: as of the Roch, Dace, Perch, &amp;c. and ſo by arte you may make many little fiſhes out of one great and naturall fiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> How to barrell vp Oyſters, ſo as they ſhall laſt for ſixe moneths ſweete and good, and in their naturall taste.</head>
               <p>OPe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your oiſters, take the licor of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and mixe a reaſonable proportion of the beſt white wine vineger you can get, a little ſalt &amp; ſome pepper, barrell the fiſh vp in ſmall caske, couering all the Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in this pickle, and they will laſt a long time; this is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent meanes to conuey Oyſters vnto drie townes, or to carie them in long voyages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> How to keepe freſh Salmon a whole moneth in his perfect taſte and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie.</head>
               <p>FIrſt ſeeth your Salmon accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vſuall manner, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinke it in apt and cloſe veſſels in wine vinegar with a braunch of Roſemarie therein. By this means Vintners and Cookes may make profit thereof when it is ſcarce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the markets, &amp; Salmon thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared may be profitably brought out of Ireland and ſold in London or elſe where.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Fiſh kept long, and yet to eate ſhorte and delicately.</head>
               <p>FRie your fiſh in oyle, ſome commend Rape Oyle, and ſome the ſweeteſt Siuill Oyle that you canne get, for the fiſh will not taſte at all of the Oyle
<pb facs="tcp:25027:67"/>becauſe it hath a watriſh bodie, &amp; oyle and water make no true vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then put your fiſh in white wine vinegar, and ſo you may keepe it for the vſe of your Table any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable-time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> How to keepe roaſted Beefe a long time ſweete and wholeſome.</head>
               <p>THis is alſo done in wine vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, your peeces being not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great, &amp; well and cloſe barrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp: this ſecret was fully proued in that honourable voyage vnto Cales.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> How to keepe powdered beefe fiue or ſix weekes after it is ſodden, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any charge.</head>
               <p>WHen your beefe hath beene well &amp; thorowly powdred by tenne or twelue dayes ſpace, then ſeeth it throughly, dry it with
<pb facs="tcp:25027:67"/>a cloth, and wrap it in dry clothes placing the ſame in cloſe veſſels and Cupbords, and it will keepe ſweete &amp; ſound two or three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, as I am credibly informed from the experience of a kinde &amp; louing friend.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>20. A</hi> conceipt of the Authors, how beefe may be carried at the ſea, with out that ſtrong and violent impreſſion of ſalt which is vſually purchaſed by long and extreme powdring.</head>
               <p>HEere with the good leaue &amp; fauour of thoſe curteous gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, for whome I did prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally if not only intend this litle treatiſe; I will make bold to lanch a little from the ſhoare, and trye what may bee done in the vaſte and wide Ocean, and in long and dangerous voyages; for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preſeruation of ſuch vſuall victuals, as for want of this skill
<pb facs="tcp:25027:68"/>doe oftentimes meerely periſh, or elſe by the extreame pearcing of the ſalte, doe loſe euen their nutritiue ſtrength and vertue: &amp; if any future experience doe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to controll my preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, let this excuſe a ſcholler, <hi>quòd in magnis eſt voluiſſe ſatis.</hi> But now to our purpoſe, let all the bloud bee firſt well gotten out of the beefe, by leauing the ſame ſome nine or tenne dayes in our vſuall brine, then barrell vp all the peeces in veſſels full of holes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening them with ropes at the ſterne of the ſhip; and ſo dragging them through the ſalte ſea water (which by his infinite change and ſucceſſion of water will ſuffer no putrifaction, as I ſuppoſe) you may happily find your beefe both ſweete and fauourie enough when you come to ſpend the ſame. And if this happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fall out true vpon ſome triall thereof had, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at my next impreſſion, or
<pb facs="tcp:25027:68"/>when I ſhall bee vrged thereunto vpon any neceſsitie of ſeruice, I hope to diſcouer the meanes alſo whereby euerie Shippe may carry ſufficient ſtore of victuall for her ſelfe in more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cloſe and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cariages then thoſe looſe veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are able to performe. But if I may be allowed to carie either roaſted or ſodden fleſh to the ſea, then I dare aduenture my poore credit therein to preſerue for ſix whole moneths together, either Beefe, Mutton, Capons, Rabbets, &amp;c. both in a cheape manner, and alſo as freſh as wee doe now vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally eate them at our Tables. And this I hold to be a moſt ſingular &amp; neceſſarie ſecret for all our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Nauie; which at all times vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon reaſonable termes I will bee ready to diſcloſe for the good of my country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> How to make ſundry ſorts of moſt dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tie butter, hauing a liuely taſte of Sage, Cinamon, Nutmegs, Mace, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THis is done by mixing a fewe drops of the extracted cyle of Sage, Cinamon, Nutmegs, Mace, &amp;c, in the making vp of your but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for oyle and butter will incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porat and agree very kindely and naturallie together. And how to make the ſaid oyles, with all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarie veſſels, inſtruments &amp; other circumſtances by a moſt pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine &amp; familiar deſcription, See my Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell houſe of Art and nature vnder the Title of diſtillation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> How to make a larger and daintier Cheeſe of the ſame proportion of milk then is commonly vſed or knowne by any of our best dairiewomen at this day.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:69"/>
               <p>HAuing brought your milke into curds by ordinarie ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, either breake them with your handes according to the vſuall manner of other cheeſes, and after with a fleeting diſh, taking away as much of the whey as you can, or els put in the curds, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breaking, into your moate, let them ſo repoſe one houre, or two, or three; and then to a cheeſe of two gallons of milk, ad a waight of tenne or twelue pound, which waight muſt reſt vppon a couer; that is fit with the moate or caſe wherein it muſt truly deſcende by degrees as you increaſe your waight, or as the curdes doe ſink and ſettle. Let your curdes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſo all that daye and night following vntil the next morning and then turne your cheeſe or curds, &amp; place your waight again theron, adding from time to time ſome more ſmall waight as you ſhall ſee cauſe. Note that you muſt
<pb facs="tcp:25027:70"/>lay a cloath both vnder and ouer your curdes at the leaſt, if you will not wrap them all ouer as they do in other cheeſes, changing your cloth at euerie turning. Alſo if you will worke in any ordinary moat, you muſt place a round and broade hoope vpon the moat, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſt of the ſelfe ſame bigneſſe or circumference, or elſe you ſhall make a verie thinne cheeſe. Turne theſe cheeſes euerie mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, or as often as you ſhall ſee cauſe, till the whey bee all run out, and then proceed as in ordinarie Cheeſes. Note that theſe moates would be full of holes, both in the ſides and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, that the whey may haue the ſpeedier paſſage. You may alſo make them in ſquare boxes full of holes, or elſe you may deuiſe moates or caſes either tounde or ſquare of fine wicker, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wicker couers, may by ſome ſlight be ſo ſtayed, as that you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:25027:70"/>neede only morning and euening to turne the wrong ſide vpwarde, both the bottomes beeing made looſe and ſo cloſe, and fitting, as they may ſinke truely within the moate or molde, by reaſon of the waight that lyeth thereon. Note that in other cheeſes the couer of the moat ſhutteth ouer the moat: but in theſe the couers deſfce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; fall within the moates. Alſo your ordinarie cheeſes are more ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and full of eyes then theſe, by reaſon of the violent presſing of them, wheras theſe cheeſes ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling gently and by degrees, do cut as cloſe and firme as marmalade. Alſo in thoſe cheeſes which are preſſed out after the vſuall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, the whey that commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, if it ſtande a while, will carrie a Creame vppon it, whereby the cheeſe muſt of neceſſitie be much leſſe, and as I gheſſe by a fourth parte, whereas the wheye that commeth from theſe new kind of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:71"/>cheeſes is like faire water in color and caryeth no ſtrength with it. Note alſo that if you put in your curdes vnbroken, not taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the whey that iſſueth in the breaking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſo the chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will yet bee ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but that is the more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome way, becauſe the curds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tender will hardly endure the turning, vnleſſe you be verie care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. I ſuppoſe that the Angelotes in Fraunce may bee made in this manner in ſmall baskets, and ſo likewiſe of the Parmeeſan; and if your whole cheeſe conſiſt of vn flatten milke, they will be full of butter and eate moſt daintily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in their time, before they be too dry, for which purpoſe you may keepe them when they begin to growe dry, vpon greene ruſhes or nettles. I haue robbed my wifes Dairy of this ſecret, who hath hitherto refuſed all recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences that haue beene offered
<pb facs="tcp:25027:71"/>her by Gentlewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame: &amp; had I loued a cheeſe my ſelfe ſo well as I like the receipt, I thinke I ſhould not ſo eaſily haue impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame at this time. And yet I muſt needes confeſſe, that for the better gracing of the Title wherewith I haue fronted this pamphlet, I haue beene willing to publiſh this with ſome other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of worth, for the which I haue many times refuſed good ſtore both of Crownes and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: and therfore let no Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman think this booke too dear, at what price ſoeuer it ſhall be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued vpon the ſale thereof, neither can I eſteeme the worke to be of leſſe then twentie yeeres gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Clouted creame.</head>
               <p>TAke your milke beeing newe milked; and preſently ſet it vpon the fire from morning vntil
<pb facs="tcp:25027:72"/>the euening, but let it not ſeethe: and this is called my Lady <hi>Youngs</hi> clowted creame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>24.</hi> Fleſh kept ſweet inſummes.</head>
               <p>YOu may keepe veale, mutton, or veniſon in the heat of ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer 9. or ten dayes good, ſo as it be newly &amp; faire killed, by han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the ſame in an high and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die roome (And therefore a plate cupboard full of holes, ſo as the wind may haue a through paſſage would be placed in ſuch a roome, to auoide the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of fly-blowes) this is an approued ſecret, eaſie and cheap, and very neceſſary to be known and practiſed in hote &amp; tainting weather. Veale may bee kept ten daies in bran.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> Muſtard meale.</head>
               <p>IT is vſuall in Venice to ſell the meale of Muſtarde in their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets
<pb facs="tcp:25027:72"/>as we do flower and meale in England: this meale by the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vinegar in two or three dayes be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth exceeding good muſtard, but it would bee much ſtronger and finer, if the husks or huls were firſt diuided by ſearce or boulter, which may eaſily bee don, if you drie your ſeeds againſt the fire before you grind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Dutch iron handmils, or an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie pepper mill may ſerue for this purpoſe. I thought it verie neceſſarie to publiſh this manner of making of your ſauce, becauſe our muſtard which wee buy from the Chandlers at this daye is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times made vp with vile and filthy vinegar, ſuch as our ſtomak would abhorre if we ſhould ſee it before the mixing therof with the ſeedes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> How to auold ſmoke, in broyling of Bacon, Carbona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>MAke little dripping pans of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:73"/>paper; paſting vp the corners with ſtarch or paſte, wet them a little in water, but Pope <hi>Pius Quiniu:</hi> his Cooke will haue them touched ouer with a feather firſt dipped in oyle or molten butter, lay them on your gridiron, &amp; place therein your ſlices of bacon, turning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as you ſee cauſe. This is a cleanly way, and auoydeth all ſmoke. In the ſame manner you may alſo broile thin ſlices of Polonian ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedges, or great oyſters, for ſo were the Popes Oyſters dreſſed. You muſt be carefull that your fire vnder the gridiron flame not, leaſt you happen to burne your drip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping pannes, and therefore all colebrands are here ſecluded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> The true bottling of beere.</head>
               <p>WHen your Beere is tenne or twelue dayes old, whereby it is growne reaſonable cleare,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:73"/>then bottle it, making your corkes verie fitte for the bottles, and ſtop them cloſe, bur drinke not of this beere till they beginne to worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and mantle, and then you ſhall finde the ſame moſt excellent and ſprightly drinke: and this is the reaſon why bottle ale is both ſo win die and muddy, thundring &amp; ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon the opening of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, becauſe it is commonly bottled the ſame day that it is laide into the Cellar, whereby his yeaſt being an exceeding windie ſubſtance, beeing alſo drawne with the Ale not yet fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, doth incorporate with the drinke, and maketh it alſo verie windie, and this is all the lime and gunpowder wherewith bottle Ale hath beene a long time ſo wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully charged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>28.</hi> How to helpe your bottles when they are mustie.</head>
               <p>SOme put them in an ouen when
<pb facs="tcp:25027:74"/>the breade is newly drawen, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp the oven, and ſo let them reſt till morning. Others content themſelues with ſcaulding them in hotte liquor onely till they bee ſweete.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> How to breake whites of Egs ſpeedily.</head>
               <p>A Figge or two ſhred in peeces, and then beaten amongſt the whites of egges will bringe them into an oyle ſpeedily: ſome breake them with a ſtubbed rod, &amp; ſome by wringing them often through a ſpoonge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>30.</hi> How to keepe flies from oyle peeces.</head>
               <p>A Line limed ouer and ſtrained about the creſt of oyle peeces or pictures, will catch they Flyes, that woulde otherwiſe deface the Pictures. But this Italian con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceipt both for the rareneſſe and
<pb facs="tcp:25027:74"/>vſe thereof doth pleaſe me aboue all other: viz, Pricke a Cowcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber full o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> barley cornes with the ſmall ſpiring ends outward, make little holes in the Cowcumber firſt with a wodden or bone bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, and after put in the graine, theſe being thicke placed will in time couer all the Cowcumber, ſo as no man can diſcerne what ſtrange plant the ſame ſhould bee. Such Cowcumbers are to bee hung vp in the middeſt of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer r omes to drawe all the flies vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which otherwiſe would flie vpon the Pictures or hang<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ings</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>31.</hi> To keepe Lobſters, Crafiſhes, &amp;c. ſweet and good for ſome fewe dayes.</head>
               <p>THeſe kinds of fiſh are noted to be of no durabilitie or laſting in warme weather, yet to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long their dayes a little, though I feare I ſhall raiſe the price of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:75"/>them by this diſcouerie amongſt the fiſhmongers (who onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their ſpeedie decay doe now and then afford a peniworth in them) if you wrappe them in ſweete and courſe rags firſt moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened in brine, and then burie theſe cloathes in Callis ſand, that is alſo kept in ſome coole and moiſt place, I know by mine owne experience that you ſhall finde your labour well beſtowed, and the rather if you lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall clothes, ſo as one doe not touch the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>32.</hi> Diuers excellent kinds of bottle Ale.</head>
               <p>I Cannot remember that euer I did drinke the like ſage ale at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time, as that which is made by mingling two or three droppes of the extracted oyle of ſage with a quart of Ale, the ſame beeing well brued out of one pot into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb facs="tcp:25027:75"/>and this way a whole Stand of ſage ale is very ſpeedily made. The like is to bee done with the oyle of Mace or Nutmegs. But if you will make a right goſsips cup that ſhall farre exceed all the Ale that euer mother <hi>Bunch</hi> made in her life time, then in the bottling vp of your beſt Ale, tunne halfe a pinte of white Ipocras that is newly made, and after the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, with a pottle of Ale, ſtoppe your bottle cloſe, and drinke it when it is ſtale: Some commend the hanging of roaſted Orenges prickt full of Cloues in the veſſell of Ale till you find the taſte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly graced to your own liking.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>33.</hi> How to make wormewood wine verie ſpeedily and in great quantity.</head>
               <p>TAke ſmall Rochell or Coniake wine, put a few droopes of the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:76"/>extracted oile of wormwood ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, brewe it togither (as before is ſet down in bottle ale) out of one pot into an other, and you ſhall haue a more neate and wholeſom wine for your body, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is ſolde at the Stillyard for right wormwood wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Roſewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er and Roſeuinegar of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the Roſe, and of the Cowſlep, and violet vinegar.</head>
               <p>IF you woulde make your Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water and Roſe vinegar of a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie color, then make choiſe of the crimſon veluet coloured leaues, clipping away the whites with a paire of ſheeres, &amp; being through dryed, put a good large handful of them into a pinte of Damaske or red roſewater, ſtop your glaſſe wel &amp; ſet it in the ſun, til you ſee that the leaues haue loſt their colour. Or for more expedition you may pecforme this worke in balneo in
<pb facs="tcp:25027:76"/>a few houres, and when you take out the olde leaues, you may put in freſh till you finde the color to pleaſe you. Keep this Roſewater in glaſſes very well ſtopt, the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler the better. What I haue ſaid of Roſewater, the ſame may alſo be intended of Roſe vinegar, violet, marigolde, and cowſlep vinegar, but the whiter vinegar you chuſe for this purpoſe, the colour ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will be the brighter, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſtilled Vinegar is beſt for this purpoſe, ſo as the ſame bee warily diſtilled with a true diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of parts, according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner expreſſed in this booke in the diſtillation of vinegar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>35.</hi> To keepe the iuice of Oranges and Lemmons al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the yeare for ſauce, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leps and other purpoſes.</head>
               <p>EXpreſſe their iuyce, and paſſe it through an Ipocraſſe bagge to clarifie it from his impurities,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:77"/>then fill your glaſſe almoſt to the top, couer it cloſely, and let it ſtand ſo till it haue done boyling; then fill vp your glaſſe with good ſallet oyle, and ſet it in a coole cloſet or butterie where no Sun commeth; the apteſt glaſſes for this purpoſe are ſtraight vpright ones, like to our long beere glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which would bee made with little round holes within two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the bottome to receiue apt fawcets, &amp; ſo the grounds or lees would ſettle to the bottome, and the oyle would ſinke downe with the iuice ſo cloſely that all putrefaction would be auoyded: or in ſteede of holes if there were glaſſe pipes it were the better &amp; readyer way, becauſe you ſhall hardly faſten a fawcet well in the hole. You may alſo in this manner preſerue many iuyces of hearbes and flowers.</p>
               <p>And becauſe that profite and skill vnited do grace each other,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:77"/>if (curteous Ladies) you will lend eares and followe my direction; I will heere furniſh a great number of you (I woulde I coulde furniſh you all) with the iuice of the beſt ciuill Orenges at an eaſie price, About Alhallontide or ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you may buy the inward pulpe of ciuill Ore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges wherin the iuice reſteth, of the comfetmakers for a ſmall matter, who doe onely or principally reſpect their rindes to preſerue and make Orengeadoes with all, this iuice you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire and reſerue as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>36.</hi> Howe to purifie and giue an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſmell and taſte vnto ſallet oyle.</head>
               <p>PVt ſallet Oyle in a Veſſell of wood or earth, hauing a hole in the bottom, to euery 4 quartes of water adde one quarte of oyle, and with a woodden ſpoone or
<pb facs="tcp:25027:78"/>ſpattle beate them well togither for a quarter of an houre, then let out the water, preuenting the oyle from iſſuing by ſtopping of the hole, repeate this worke two or three times, and at the laſt you ſhall finde your oile wel clenſed or clarified. In this maner you may alſo clarifie capons greaſe, being firſt melted, and workinge with warm vvater. All this is borrowed of <hi>M. Bartholomaeus Scapius</hi> the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Cook of Pope <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> his priuie kitchen. I thinke if the laſt agitation were made in Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherin alſo cloues or Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs had been macerated, that ſo the oyle woulde bee yet more pleaſing.</p>
               <p>Or if you ſet a Iar glaſſe in bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo full of ſweete oyle with ſome ſtore of bruiſed cloues, and rinds of ciuil Oranges or Lemmons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo therein, and ſo continue your fire for tvvo or three houres, and then letting the Clouès &amp; rindes
<pb facs="tcp:25027:78"/>remain in the oile til both the ſent &amp; taſte do pleaſe you: I think ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny men which at this day do loath oile (as I my ſelfe did not long ſince) woulde be eaſily drawen to a ſufficient liking thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>37.</hi> How to clarifie without any diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion both white and &amp; claret wine vinegar for gellies or ſauces.</head>
               <p>TO euerie ſixe pintes of good wine vinegar, put the whites of tvvo new laid Egges wel beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then put all into a nevve leaden pipkin, &amp; cauſe the ſame to boyle a little ouer a gentle fire, then let it run through a courſe gelly bag twiſe or thriſe, and it vvill be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry clear, and keep good one whole yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>38.</hi> To make a moſt delicate white ſalte for the table.</head>
               <p>FIrſt calcine or burn your white
<pb facs="tcp:25027:79"/>ſalt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſſolue it in cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit water, let the water ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtirring, fortie eight houres, then carefully drawe away all the cleare water only, filter it, &amp; after euaporate the filtred liquor, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the ſalt. Some leaue out calcination.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>39. A</hi> delicate Candle for a Ladies Table.</head>
               <p>CAuſe your Dutch Candles to be dipped in Virgin wax, ſo as their laſt coate may be meerly waxe, and by this meanes, you may carrie them in your hande without melting, and the ſent of the tallow will not break through to giue offence, but if you would haue them to reſemble yellovve waxe candles, then firſt let the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low be colored with Turmericke boyled therein, and ſtrayned, and after your Candles haue beene dipped therein to a ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:25027:79"/>greatneſſe, let them take their laſt coate from yellow waxe, this may be done in a great round Cane of tinne plate, hauing a bottome, &amp; being ſomewhat deeper then the length of your candles: &amp; as the wax ſpendeth, you may ſtill ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it with more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>40.</hi> How to hang your candles in the aire without candleſticke.</head>
               <p>THis will make a ſtrange ſhewe to the beholders that knowe not the conceite, it is done in this manner: Let a fine Virginall wier be conueied, in the midſt of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie weeke and left of ſome length aboue the Candle to faſten the ſame to the poſtes in the roofe of your houſe, and if the roome be any thing high roofed, it will be hardly diſcerned, and the flame though it conſume the tallow, yet it will not melt the wier.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:80"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>41.</hi> Roſe Vinegar made in a new manner.</head>
               <p>MAcerate or ſteepe Roſe-leaues in faire water, let them lye therein, til they wax ſoure in ſmell, and then diſtill the water.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:80"/>
            <head>SWEETE Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, oyntments, <hi>beauties, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>1.</hi> An excellent damaſk powder</head>
            <p>TAke of yreos halfe a pounde, Roſe leaues 4. ounces, cloues one ounce, lignum Rhodium two ounces, Storax one ounce and a halfe, muske and ciuet of each 10 grains, beat and incorporate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well together.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> An excellent hand water or waſhing water very cheape.</head>
               <p>TAke a gallon of faire water, one handful of Laue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, a few cloues, and ſome orace
<pb facs="tcp:25027:81"/>powder, and foure ounces of Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin; diſtill the water in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie leaden ſtill: You may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill a ſecond water by a newe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of water vpon the feces, a little of this will ſweeten a baſon of faire water for your table.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>3. A</hi> ball to take out ſtaines from linnen.</head>
               <p>TAke foure ounces of white hard Soape, beate it in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar with two ſmall Lemmons ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and as much roche allome as an hafell Nut, roll it vp in a ball, rub the ſtaine therewith, and after fetch it out with warme water if neede be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>4. A</hi> ſwéete and delicate Pomander.</head>
               <p>TAke two ounces of Labdanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of Beniamin and Storax one ounce, muske ſixe graines, ciuet
<pb facs="tcp:25027:81"/>ſixe graines, Amber greece ſixe graines, of Calamus Aromaticus and Lignum Aloes, of each the waight of a groat, beat all theſe in a hote mortar, and with an hote peſtell till they come to paſte, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wet your hand with roſe water, &amp; roll vp the paſte ſodainly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>5. To</hi> take ſtaines out of ones hands preſently.</head>
               <p>THis is done with the iuyce of Sorrell, waſhing the ſtained place therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> To take away ſpots and freckles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face or hands.</head>
               <p>THe ſappe that iſſueth out of a Birch tree in great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, being opened in March or Aprill, with a receiuer of glaſſe ſet vnder the boring thereof to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſame, doth perform the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:82"/>ſame moſt excellently &amp; maketh the skin very cleare. This ſap will diſſolue pearl, a ſecret not known vnto many.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>7. A</hi> white fucus or beauty for the face.</head>
               <p>THe iawe bones of a Hogge or Sow well burnt, beaten, and ſearced through a fine ſearce, and after grounde vpon a porphire or ſerpentine ſtone is an excellent fucus, being laid on with the oyle of white poppey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>8. A</hi> delicate waſhing ball.</head>
               <p>TAke three ounces of Orace, halfe an ounce of Cypres, two ounces of Calamus Aromaticus, one ounce of Roſe leaues, two ounces of lauender flowers, beat all theſe together in a mortar, ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them through a fine ſearce,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:82"/>then ſcrape ſome caſtill ſope, and diſſolue it with ſome Roſewater, then incorporat all your powders therewith by labouring of them well in a mortar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Damaske powder.</head>
               <p>TAke fiue ounces of orace, two ounces of Cipres, two ounces of Calamus; halfe an ounce of Cloues, one ounce of Beniamin, one ounce of Roſe leaues, one ounce of Storax calamitum, halfe an ounce of Spike flowers, mixe them well together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>10. To</hi> keepe the teeth both white and ſound.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of hony, as much Vinegar, and halfe ſo much white wine, boyle them together and waſh your teeth therwith now and then.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11. To</hi> delay heat, and cleare the face.</head>
               <p>TAke three pintes of conduit water, boyle therein two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of French barly, change your water, and put in the barly again: repeate this ſo long, till your wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purchaſe no colour from the Barley, but become verie cleare: boyle the laſt three pintes to a quart, then mixe halfe a pinte of white wine therein, and when it is cold, wring the iuyce of two or three good Lemmons therein, &amp; vſe the ſame for the Morphewe, heate of the face or hands, and to cleere the skinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Skinne kept white and cleare.</head>
               <p>VVAſh the face and body of a ſucking child with breaſt milke, or Cowe milke, or mixed
<pb facs="tcp:25027:83"/>with water, euerie night, and the childes skinne will wax faire and cleare, and reſiſt ſunburning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>13. An</hi> excellent Pomatum to clear the skinne.</head>
               <p>WAſh Barrowes greaſe often times in <hi>May</hi> dewe that hath bin clarified in the ſun, till it bee exceeding white, then take Marſh mallow rootes ſcraping off the outſides, then make thin ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of them and mixe them, ſet them to macerate in a ſeething balneo, and ſcumme it well till it bee throughly clarified and will come to roap, then ſtraine it, and put now and then a ſpooneſull of May-dewe therein, bearing it till it be through cold in often cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of May-dew, then throw away that dewe, and put it in a glaſſe coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with May-dewe, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it to your vſe. Let the mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb facs="tcp:25027:84"/>rootes be two or three daies dryed in the ſhade before you vſe them. This I had of a great profeſ ſour of Arte, and for a rare and dainty ſecret, as the beſt fucus this day in vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Another minerall ficusſor the face.</head>
               <p>INcorporate vvith a woodden peſtle and in a woodden mortar with great labour foure ounces of ſublimate, and one ounce of crude Mercury at the leaſt ſixe or eight houres (you cannot beſtowe too much labor herein) then with often change of colde water by ablution in a glaſſe, take awaie the ſalts from the ſublimate, change your water twiſe euery day at the I-aſt, and in ſeauen or eight daies (the more the better) it will bee culcified, and then it is prepared. Lay it on with the oyle of white poppey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> To take away chilblanes out of the hands or feete.</head>
               <p>BOyle halfe a pecke of Oates in a quart of water, till they waxe drie, then hauing firſt annointed your handes with ſome good Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum &amp; well chafed them, hold them within the oates as hotte as you may well ſuffer them, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the bowle wherein you put your handes with a double cloth to keep in the ſteame of the oats. Do this three or foure times, and you ſhal finde the effect. The ſame Oates wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l ſerue to bee ſodden with freſhe water three or foure times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> To helpe a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that is red or pimpled.</head>
               <p>DIſſolue common ſalte in the iuice of Lemmons, and with a
<pb facs="tcp:25027:85"/>linnen cloth, pat the patients face that is full of heate or pimples. It cureth in a few dreſſings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>17. <hi>Aliter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of thoſe little whelkes or ſhels which ſome do call giny money, waſh fiue or ſixe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; beate them to fine powder, and infuſe the iuyce of Lemmons vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, &amp; it will preſently boyl: but if it offer to boyle out of your glaſſe, then ſtop the mouth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with your finger, or blow into it. This will in a ſhort time bee like an ointment, with which you muſt anoint the heate or pimples of the face often times in a daye till you find helpe. As the ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dryeth put more iuyce of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to it I his of an outlandiſh Gentlewoman, and it is an aſiured remedy if the heate bee not very extreme. Some haue found by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:85"/>that bathing of the face with hote vinegar euery night when they go to bed doth migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily repell the humour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>18. <hi>Aliter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>QVilt baye ſalte well dryed and powdered, in double linnen ſockes of a prettie bigneſſe, let the patient weare them in wide hoſe and ſhooes day and night, by the ſpace of fourteene dayes, or till he be well: euery morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning let him drie his ſockes by the fire and put them on againe. This helped M. <hi>Foſter</hi> an Eſſex ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and an Atturney of the Common pleas within theſe few yeares, but now deceaſed, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe face was for many yeares together of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinge highe and firye colour, of my owne knowledge, and had ſpent much money in Phyſicke without anie ſucceſſe at all, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:25027:86"/>he obtained his remedie. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient muſt not take any wet of his feete during the cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Aliter &amp; optime.</head>
               <p>TAke halfe a pound of white di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled vinegar, two newe laid Egges with their ſhelles, two ſpoonfuls of the flowers of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, let theſe macerate in the vinegar by the ſpace of three dayes: then take out the Egges, and pricke them ful of holes with a needle, but not too deepe, leaſt any of the yolke ſhoulde happen alſo to iſſue, let that liquor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo mixe with the vinegar, then ſtraine all through a fine cloath, and tye vp the brimſtone in the cloth like a little ball, dippe this ball in the ſtrained liquor, when you vſe it, and pat it on the place three or foure times euerie daye,
<pb facs="tcp:25027:86"/>and this will cure any red face in twelue or fourteene dayes. Some do alſo commende the ſame for an approued remedie againſt the morphew; the brimſtone bal muſt be kept in ſome cloſe thing from the ayre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> How to take away any pimple from the face.</head>
               <p>BRimſtone ground with the oyl of Turpentine, and applied to any pimple one houre, maketh the fleſh to riſe ſpungeous, which being annointed with the thicke oyle of butter that ariſeth in the morning from new milke ſodden a little ouer night, will heale and ſcale away in a fewe daies, leauing a faire skinne behinde. This is a good skinning ſalue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> To helpe any Morphew, ſunbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, itch, or red face.</head>
               <p>STeepe two ſliced Lemmons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing large and faire in a pinte of Condu it water, leaue them foure or fiue daies in infuſion couering the water, then ſtraine the water, and diſſolue therein the quantitie of a haſell nut of ſublimate (ſome hold a dramme a good proportion to a pinte of water) finely pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: let the patient wet a cloth therein, and rub the place where the griefe is euery morninge and euening a little, till the hew doe pleaſe hee: you may make the ſame ſtronger or weaker accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to good diſcretion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> For the Morphew.</head>
               <p>TAke a pinte of diſtilled vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, laie therein two newe laid
<pb facs="tcp:25027:87"/>egges whole with their ſhelles, three yellowe Docke rootes pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ſliced, two ſpoonefulls of the flowers of brimſtone, and ſo let all reſt three daies, and then vſe this liquour with a cloth, rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the place three or 4. times euerie daye, and in three or foure dayes it commonly helpeth: put ſome bran in your cloth before you moiſten your cloth therein, binding it vp in forme of a little ball. This of Maiſter <hi>Rich</hi> of Lee, who helped himſelfe and a gallant Ladie therewith in a few dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> To take away the freckles in the face.</head>
               <p>WAſh your face in the wane of the moon with a ſpunge, morninge and euening with the diſtilled water of elder leaues, lettinge the ſame drie into the skinne. Your water muſt bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled
<pb facs="tcp:25027:88"/>in <hi>Maie.</hi> This is of a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailer, who hath cured himſelfe thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>24.</hi> To cure any extreame bruiſe vpon a ſire fall, on the face, or any other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the body.</head>
               <p>PReſently after the fall make a greate fire, and applie hote cloathes one after another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſsion, the patient ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding neere the fire for one houre and a halfe, or till the ſwelling be cleane abated. This I knewe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with good ſucceſſe in a maid that fell downe a paire of ſtaires, whereby all her face was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dis figured. Some holde opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the ſame may bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed with clothes wet in hote water and wroonge out againe before application. Then to take away the chaungeable colours, which doe accuſtomablie followe all bruiſes, ſhred the roote of a
<pb facs="tcp:25027:88"/>greene or growing flower deluce, beate it with red roſe water, and grinde it till it come to a ſalue, apply the ſame, &amp; in a fewe houres it taketh away all the colours: but if it lie too long it will rayſe pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and therefore ſo ſoone as the colours be vaniſhed, immediately remooue the ſalue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> How to keepe the teeth cleane.</head>
               <p>CAlcine the tops and branches of Roſemarie into aſhes, and to one part there of, put one part of burnt allome, mixe them well together, and with thy finger firſt moiſtened a little with thy ſpettle, rubbe all thy teeth ouer a prettie while euerie morning till they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be cleane, but not to galling of thy gums, then ſup vp ſome fair water or white wine, gargling the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vp &amp; down thy mouth a while, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25027:89"/>drie thy mouth with a towel. This of an honeſt Gentleman and a painefull gatherer of phyſicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Sweet and delicate dentifrices or Rubbers for the teeth.</head>
               <p>DIſſolue in foure ounces of warme water, three or foure drammes of gumme Dragagant, and in one night this will become a thicke ſubſtance like gellie, mingle the ſame with the powder of Alablaſter finely grounde and fearced, then make vp this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance into little round rolles, of the bigneſſe of a childes arrowe, &amp; foure or fiue inches in length. Alſo if you temper Roſet or ſome other colour (that is not hurtful) with them, they will ſhew ful of pleaſing veines. Theſe you may ſweeten either with Roſewater, Ciuet, or muske. But if your teeth
<pb facs="tcp:25027:89"/>be verie ſcaly, let ſome exper barbar firſt take off the ſcales with his inſtrument, and then you may keepe them cleane by rubbing them with the aforeſaide rolles. And heere, by thoſe miſerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences that I haue ſeene in ſome of my neereſt friendes, I am inforced to admoniſh all Gentled women to be carefull howe they ſuffer their teeth to bee cleanſed and made white with anie <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> which is the Barbars vſuall water: for vnleſſe the ſame be both well delayed, and carefullie appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhee may happen within a fewe dreſsings to be forced to borrow a ranke of teeth to eate her din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, vnleſſe her gums do helpe her the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> A delicate ſtoue to ſweat in.</head>
               <p>I Know that many Gentlewomen as well for the clearing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their
<pb facs="tcp:25027:90"/>skins as cleanſing of their bodies, do now and then delight to ſweat. For the which purpoſe I haue ſet downe this manner following, as the beſt that euer I obſerued. Put into a braſſe pot of ſome good content, ſuch proportion of ſweet hearbes, and of ſuch kind as ſhall bee moſt appropriate for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, with ſome reaſonable quantitie of water, cloſe the ſame with an apt couer, and well luted with ſome paſte made of flower and whites of Egges: at ſome parte of the couer you muſt let in a leaden pipe (the entraunce whereof muſt alſo bee well luted) this pipe muſt bee conueyed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the ſide of the Chimney, where the pot ſtandeth in a thicke hollow ſtake, of a bathing tubb croſſed with hoopes according to the vſual manner in the top, which you may couer with a ſheete at your pleaſure. Nowe the ſteame of the pot paſsing thorough the
<pb facs="tcp:25027:90"/>pipe vnder the falſe bottome of the bathing tub, which muſt bee boared full of bigge boles, will breath ſo ſweete and warme a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour vpon your bodie, as that (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing aire by holding your head without the tub as you fit therin) you ſhall ſweat moſt temperately, and continue the ſame a longe time without fainting. And this is performed with a ſmall charcoale fire maintained vnder the pot for this purpoſe. Note that the room would be cloſe wherein you place your bathing tub, leaſt any ſodain cold ſhould happen to offend you whileſt your bodie is made open and porous to the aire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Diuers ſorts of ſweet or hand waters made ſodainly or extempore, with the extracted oyles of ſpices.</head>
               <p>FIrſt you ſhall vnderſtande that whenſoeuer you ſhall drawe
<pb facs="tcp:25027:91"/>any of the aforeſaid oyles of Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Cloues, Mace, Nutmegs or ſuch like, that you ſhall haue alſo a pottle, or a gallon more or leſſe, according to the quantity which you drawe at once, of excellent ſweete waſhing water for your ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yea ſome do keepe the ſame for their broths, wherein other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſhould vſe ſome of the ſame kind of ſpice. But if you take three or foure drops onely of the oyle of Cloues, Mace, or Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs (for Cinamon oyle is too coſtly to ſpend this way) and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle the ſame with a pinte of faire water, making agitation of them a prettie while together in a glaſſe hauing a narrowe mouth, till they haue in ſome meaſure incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues together, you ſhall find a verie pleaſing and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full water to waſh with, and ſo you may alwayes furniſh your ſelfe of ſweete water of ſeuerall kindes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch time as your gueſts ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:25027:91"/>bee readie to ſit downe. I ſpeak not here of the oile of ſpike, which will extend verie farre this waye, both becauſe euerie gentlewoman doth not like ſo ſtronge a ſent, and for that the ſame is elſwhere alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy commended by another Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. Yet I muſt needes acknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be the cheaper way, for that I aſſure my ſelfe there may be fiue or ſix gallons of ſweete wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter made with one ounce of the oile, which you may buy ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily for a groate at the moſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>29.</hi> An excellent ſweet water for a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bottle.</head>
               <p>TAke three drams of oile of Spike, one dramme of oyle of Thyme, one dram of oyle of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, one dram of oile of cloues, then take one graine of Ciuet, and three graines of the aforeſaid compoſition well wrought toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:25027:92"/>Temper them well in a ſiluer ſpoone with your finger, then put the ſame into a ſiluer boll, waſhing it out by little and little into the boll with a little Roſewater at once, til all the oyle be waſhed out of the ſpoone into the boule, and then doe the like by waſhing the ſame out of the boule with a little Roſewater at once, till all the ſent be gotten out, putting the Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water ſtill in a glaſſe, when you haue tempered the ſame in the boule ſufficiently. A pinte of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water will bee ſufficient to mingle with the ſaid proportion: and if you finde the ſame not ſtronge e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of the ciuet, then you may to euery pinte put one graine and a halfe, or two graines of ciuer to the weight of three graines of the aforeſaide compoſition of oyles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>30.</hi> To colour a blacke haire preſently into a Cheſnut colour.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:92"/>
               <p>THis is done with oyle of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oll, but you muſt doe it verie carefully not touching the skin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>31. A</hi> preſent and delicate perfume.</head>
               <p>LAy two or three droppes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Amber vpon a glowing coale, or a peece of lignum aloes, lignum Rhodium, or ſtorax.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>32.</hi> To renew the ſent of a Pomander.</head>
               <p>TAke one graine of ciuet, and two of muske, or if you dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the proportion it will bee ſo much the ſweeter, grind them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſtone with a little Roſewater, and after wetting your hands with Roſewater, you may worke the ſame in your Pomander. This is a ſleight to paſſe away an olde Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, but my intention is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:93"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>33.</hi> How to gather and clarifie May-dewe.</head>
               <p>VVHen there hath fallen no rain the night before, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a cleane and large ſponge, the next morning you may gather the ſame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſweet hearbs, graſſe, or corne: ſtraine your dewe, and expoſe it to the ſunne in glaſſes couered with papers or parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prickt full of holes, ſtrain it often, continuing it in the ſun, and in an hote place till the ſame growe white and cleere, which wil require the beſt parte of the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Some commend May dewe gathered from Fennell and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landine, to be moſt excellent for ſore eyes, &amp; ſome commend the ſame (prepared as before) aboue Roſewater for preſeruing of fruits flowers, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:93"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Diuers excellent ſentes for gloues, with their proportions and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, with the manner of perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</head>
               <p>THe Violet, the Orenge, the Lemmon duely proportioned with other ſentes, performe this well, ſo likewiſe of Labdanum, Storax, Beniamin. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The manner is this. Firſt lay your vmber vpon a few coales till it begin to cracke like lime, then let it coole of it ſelfe, taking away the coales, then grinde the ſame with ſome yellowe ocre, till you perceiue a right color for a gloue: with this mixture waſh ouer your gloue with a little haire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruſh vpon a ſmooth ſtone in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſeame and all ouer, then hang your gloues to drie vppon a line, then with gum Dragagant diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſome Roſewater, &amp; ground with a little oyle de Ben, or of
<pb facs="tcp:25027:94"/>ſweet Almonds vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtone, ſtrike ouer your gloues in euerie place with the gum and oyle ſo ground together, doe this with a little ſpoonge, but bee ſure the gloues be firſt throughly dry, and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour well rubbed and beaten out of the gloue; then let them hange againe till they be drie, which will be in a ſhort time. Then if you will haue your gloue to lie ſmooth and faire in ſhewe, goe ouer it againe with your ſpoonge, and the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of gumme and oyle, and drie the gloue yet once againe. Then grinde vppon your ſtone two or three graines of good muske, with halfe a ſpoonefull of Roſewater, and with a verie little peece of a ſpoonge take vp the compoſition by a little and little, and ſo lay it vpon your gloue lying vppon the ſtone. Picke and ſtraine your gum Dragagant before you vſe it. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume but the one ſide of your gloue at once, and then hang it vp
<pb facs="tcp:25027:94"/>to drie, and then finiſh the other ſide. Tenne graines of muske wil giue a ſufficient perfume to eight paire of gloues. Note alſo that this perfume is done vpon a thin Lambes leather gloue, and if you worke vpon a kids skin or goates skin, which is vſuall leather for rich perfumes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you muſt adde more quantitie of the oyle of Ben to your gumme, and go ouer the gloue twiſe therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Sweet bags to lie among linnen.</head>
               <p>FIll your bags only with lignum Rhodium finely beaten, and it will giue an excellent ſent to your linnen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>36.</hi> To make haire of a faire yellowe or golden colour.</head>
               <p>THe laſt water that is drawne from honey being of a deepe red colour performeth the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:25027:95"/>excellently, but the ſame hath a ſtrong ſmell, and therefore muſt be ſweetned with ſome aromatical bodie.</p>
               <p>Or elſe the haire beeing firſt cleane waſhed and then moiſtned a prettie while by a good fire in warme allum water with a ſpunge, you may moiſten the ſame in a decoctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Turmericke, rubarb, or the barke of the Barberie tree, and ſo it will receiue a moſt faire and beautifull colour. The Dog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> berrie is alſo an excellent berrie to make a golden liquor withall for this purpoſe, beate your allum to powder, and when the water is ready to ſeeth, diſſolue it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: foure ounces to a pottle of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will be ſufficient, let it boyle a while, ſtraine it, and this is your allom licour wherewith you muſt firſt prepare the haire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>37.</hi> How to colour the head or beard in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Cheſnut colour in halfe an houre.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25027:95"/>
               <p>TAke one part of lead calcined with ſulphur, and one parte of quicke lime, temper them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thin with water, lay it vpon the haire, chafing it well in, and let it dry one quarter of an houre or thereabout, then waſh the ſame off with faire water diuers times, and laſtly, with ſoape and water, and it will be a verie naturall haire colour. The longer it lyeth vpon the haire the browner it groweth. This coloureth not the fleſh at all, and yet it laſteth verie long in the haire. <hi>Saepius expertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:97"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25027:97"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
